PNC has a choice to make:
invest in the future.
And that's in wind energy
and renewable energies in alternative economies.
I've been to countless
demonstrations and marches and protests and rallys in
various places and in my early days mostly with my dad.
What is that meant for me?
I think it means it's a place I feel really comfortable.
It's a place I feel pretty at home
and it's part of my belief of what democracy is about.
It's part of my belief of what Quakerism is about.
My dad has tremendous integrity.
He practices what he preaches
and he's willing to put it on the line.
Who are these quakers?
Is it that guy on the Quaker box?
Do you still wear the big hats
and do you have the big, burly beards?
Are you like the Amish?
Do you still ride in buggies?
How are modern quakers different from long ago?
Some of my students really know about equality and integrity
and some of the testimonies like peace testimony,
that is fundamental to Quakers today.
How has the past informed the present
and how will the president inform the future?
The Quaker on the cereal box is actually a Presbyterian
oatmeal company who decided to use a Quaker image
because it's associated with reliability and quality.
This is in the late 19th century,
by which time Quakers have become very integrated in society,
have become very successful at business.
And so by that point, the image of a Quaker would convey
quality, reliability, integrity.
There's an advice from George fox stated 1670
about not making an undue profit,
but they're being a fair price for something.
And so quakers would sell things at a fixed price,
not haggar when they were buying things.
And this led to a great respect amongst the wider population
for Quaker integrity and honesty.
And people started to trust quakers with their money and say,
"Well, will you look after this?",
because they knew they would get it back.
And from that, you get
Quakers being involved in the sort of
nascent banking industry.
In 1915,
Friends actually tried to get a law through Congress
which would have made it illegal to use the name
of a religious denomination for commercial purposes.
But unfortunately for Friends,
Quaker Oats had enough lobbying power to kill the bill.
And so Quaker continued to be a
rather powerful advertising symbol.
So I would guess since the late 19th century,
they've made billions on billions of dollars.
For nearly 400 years,
Quakers have been led by their basic testimonies:
simplicity, peace, equality, integrity, stewardship of the earth.
Inward looking, they are directed by the mystical belief
that there is that of God in every person.
They also look outward, seeking to change the world.
All quakers are not the same.
There are silent unprogrammed Quaker meetings,
but also Evangelical Quakered churches with pastors and choirs.
Quakers are found in the Americas,
Europe, the Middle East, Asia and the Pacific.
But today more than half of the religious
Society of Friends live in Africa.
This remarkable growth began in 1902
when Evangelical Quaker missionaries from Ohio travel to Kenya.
Despite these different forms of worship,
it is their common testimony to peace
that unites Quakers throughout the world.
I went to see a movie about mountaintop removal
coal mining and there was an interview with a woman
talking about when she puts her child in a bathtub,
she knows that there's arsenic in that water.
And I'm thinking,
"Let's do a nonviolent direct action campaign".
This is something that's in Quaker DNA.
That segregation be ended...
We've done it before.
We can do it again.
It took a proud daughter of New Jersey, Alice Paul,
years of organizing marches
and hunger strikes and protests
and drafting hundreds of pieces of legislation
and writing letters and giving speeches
and working with congressional leaders
before she and other suffragists finally
helped win women the right to vote.
If you were to put together
a kind of hall of fame of American activists,
whether it be the peace movement,
whether it be women's suffrage or abolitionism,
it really is striking when you look at those names,
how many of them either were themselves Quakers
or who were influenced by Quaker principles.
I'm not sure if Quakers would have
described themselves as revolutionaries
but they're certainly trying to
establish the kingdom of God on earth.
They believe that heaven will be established on earth.
It's a spiritual warfare, what they call the Lamb's War,
a reference to the book of Revelation.
George Fox came into this group
and was seen as a potential leader and a prophetic voice.
From what we can gather,
he was very charismatic.
He was a tall,
very powerfully-built man,
and I think people were prepared to listen to him.
And he won them over.
He convinced many people quite quickly.
In 1652, George fox comes here to pendle hill and
says he's moved by the lord
and he has a vision of a great people to be gathered.
We could really date that vision
as the beginning of quakerism,
as a church, as a movement.
And what he discovers is that
he can have a direct relationship with God.
And this is really foundational for Quakerism
and becomes the fundamental belief,
that they don't need a minister or a book
to tell them what is of God.
Everybody is to be a minister, essentially,
It's a very open and universal message
that something new is happening for the people of England.
Quakers of course are part of the historic peace church movement
with Mennonites and Brethren,
they've been part of the civil rights movement,
they've been followers of Gandhi and civil disobedience at times.
And they've been key in the role of petition and lobby
to try and change government minds over 3 and 1/2 centuries
The basic principles of Quakerism
did not initially include pacifism or the peace testimony
but soon it became one of the core beliefs
that was not negotiable to the early Quakers.
I am generally suspected to be
a common disturber of the nation's peace,
"an enemy to the king and that I,
with others endeavor to raise insurrections
to embroil the nation in blood",
"All of which is utterly false,
and I do in every part deny it,
for my weapons are spiritual,
which take away the occasion of war and lead into peace".
He was brought before the court for his preaching in 1650.
Even then, he is seen as a dangerous preacher.
And so the judge says to him,
"Do you not quake before God?".
And George Fox says,
"Yes, you should as well".
And it was seen as a derogatory named to be called a Quaker,
and it was really the early 20th century
before Quaker started to think,
"All right, well, we'll own it".
You know, "We'll be Guakers".
And so this is where this...
and we are all happily Quakers now,
but I dare say if you've gone back to the 18th century,
they would most certainly not have been happy about being quakers.
They were the Religious Society of Friends.
Fox saw women as equal to men in the eyes of God.
Women, like men, could be ministers,
speaking publicly for their faith.
That's been a huge gift to me
is how powerful women are in Quakerism,
and that the power of women has not...
at least in my experience been held down,
but been really welcomed.
So learning what it means to be a Quaker feminist...
but I had some great teachers.
Margaret Fell is one of the key early Quaker leaders
and a symbol
of women's leadership in the early Quaker movement.
She writes letters and tracts
theologically sophisticated and very compelling.
She wrote one called "Women's speaking justified",
arguing for the right of women to preach.
She provided a safe haven
at her home at Swarthmore hall,
financial support and assistance to George fox and others.
My feeling is that if Margaret Fell had not stepped forward
with the kinds of material support that she provided,
that it's unlikely that George Fox could have succeeded.
She herself is put into jail.
She has a land stripped away from her at one point.
And she says,
"Although I'm no longer under the king's protection,
I know I'm under God's".
Generally, I think the women preachers did have a tougher time,
because, of course, women preaching themselves was unusual.
The trembling and shaking that came with Quakerism
was seen to be some kind of dangerous hysteria.
One of the punishments which some Quakers
would have been subjected to...
and in particular, Quaker women would be the scold's bridle.
And essentially, it is a cage
that fits over the person's head.
With a metal bar inside that goes over the tongue.
They would be taken to the marketplace
as the other person led them around.
They were pulling on the chain which made the cage move.
And as it moved, the metal bar moved inside the mouth,
which meant that teeth were broken,
jaws were occasionally broken, absolute agony.
The followers of Quakerism, hundreds of them,
would be held in the common room in Lancaster Prison.
They would speak to each other.
They would create among themselves...
a very strong solidarity of resistance to the government.
Something that I think has been
perpetrated through the centuries in Quakerism,
and that goes back to the common room
at Lancaster prison in the late 1600s.
Probably about 11,000 a put in prison during this time
and over 400 die in prison in those 3 decades.
The strong solidarity they developed
as a result of this carried them
onward into America with even more religious resolve.
Their experience in English prisons filthy,
crowded and dangerous...
led them to join in the recreation of prison reform,
first in Philadelphia's, Walnut Street Jail
and then in the city's massive Eastern State Penitentiary.
They introduced the concept of single prisoner
confinement with a light in each cell
from a small opening in this ceiling,
suggesting the prisoner could benefit from exposure to the Divine.
The only book in their cell was a bible,
to pray for forgiveness, reconcile their past and start anew.
This solution may have worked for Quakers,
but many others who found themselves isolated
for weeks, months and years saw it as mental torture.
This was a whopper of an unintended consequence.
Yet there are still now tens of thousands of men and women
shut away in solitary confinement in American prisons.
Most people in the United States would probably
associate the concentration of Quakers with the Delaware Valley.
Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
But there were large numbers of Quakers
in the Carolinas already in the 1660s.
They were escaping the persecutions of Qakers in New England.
Puritans weren't big fans of Quakers.
Quakers didn't pay their church tithes.
They didn't support the ordain clergy.
They wouldn't serve in the militia because of their testimonies.
So they weren't much welcome in New England.
And in fact, in 1660, four quakers were hanged
on Boston Common simply for being Quaker.
Not the quakers bear grudges,
but we can still name them:
Mary Dyer, William Robinson,
William Leddra and Marmaduke Stephenson.
Some early colonies were opened to accepting other faiths,
like Rhode Island in New England,
in the South, North Carolina was also more welcoming.
And then there was Pennsylvania,
founded by William Penn in 1681.
Penn is very unlike any of the other early Friends.
He's from a well-to-do background.
His father is an admiral and moving in aristocratic circles.
He is educated at Oxford,
but whilst his at Oxford,
starts to pick up some radical religious ideas.
And his father's not very happy about this,
takes him out of Oxford.
It was against the law
to publicly preach and defend quakerism in England.
Penn was sent to prison 4 times.
His most famous book, "No cross, no crown",
in which he admonishes the king,
was written in 1668
while serving a sentence in the Tower of London.
As a repayment of a debt to his father, Admiral Penn,
Charles II grants the land that now we know
as Pennsylvania to William Penn,
and he becomes the proprietor of Pennsylvania.
Why would a king grant this much territory
to one person at this particular time?
And one of the theories is that
they would have been very happy
if these troublesome Quakers would have packed up
and left England.
By some accounts,
William Penn becomes, in 1681,
the largest private landowner in the world.
Penn sets up what we would call the Holy Experiment,
a desire to have a state that's run on Godly principles,
where religious toleration is guaranteed.
Penn's frame of government
granted significant religious freedom,
though not with a guarantee of civil liberties for all.
Voting and office-holding
were restricted to white male Christians.
Penn extended his belief in toleration
to relations with the Indians.
He met with tribal leaders,
respected the rights of Native Americans to live on the land,
and paid for the land purchased from them.
Sadly, that lofty vision was not to be fulfilled.
Quakers found themselves unable
to control others who came to Pennsylvania,
hungry for land and finally withdrew all together
from trying to enforce those early treaties.
Pennsylvania was not the peaceable kingdom
and Penn himself was quite disappointed
in the way the place developed.
It developed more or less like
lots of other political communities with factions and disputes
and arguments over money and land and all the rest.
William Penn was a man of his time and owned about 9 slaves.
We only know that he gave at least one named Yaffe  his freedom.
30 years before Penn's death,
some Quakers had already begun speaking out against slavery.
- Wanna try?	- Sure.
Almost at the outset quakers saw slaves as sharing the inner light.
Remarkably, William Penn spent only
4 years in his beloved Pennsylvania.
Legal conflicts over land rights in America and Ireland
brought him back to England in 1702.
He died in extreme debt in 1718 at the age of 73.
but his influence on america's future path of tolerance
equality and freedom was immeasurable.
Even as quakers gained power, there was a reaction:
the Quietest period,
driven by Quakers who now became more exclusive and restrictive.
Most historians look at the beginning of the Quietest period
coming around at late 1600s,
early 1700s and lasting into the middle of the 1800s,
about 150 year period.
And marrying out or marrying a non-Quaker was not allowed.
It was a disown-able offense,
or it was something that if you did,
then you could be dropped from your membership.
Dolley Payne,  who's more properly known as Dolly Madison,
was born into a Quaker family in New Garden, North Carolina.
Her first husband was a Quaker,
and then her husband died of the yellow fever.
And when she remarried,
she married a non-Quaker, James Madison,
and she was dropped from membership.
But she did maintain an affection
for the Society of Friends throughout her life.
Although she didn't dress overly Quakerly,
if you take a look at her portraits.
She was quite fashionable
and was known as quite a hostess in the White House.
Just as the Quietest supposed marrying out,
their strict beliefs even banned art, music and fiction.
The aversion to art, to music is not new.
Early Quakers were very very firm on this.
It took many centuries before
Friends started to warm up even to novels.
The great abolitionist Lucretia Mott
would not read "Uncle Tom's cabin" even though
she admired the work of the author,
because it was a novel and it was not true.
So we are evolving from that.
Here in this silence,
people wait for a leading from the Divine to speak.
There is no pastor.
Everyone is a minister and shares that responsibility.
Come into my Father's house.
Come into God's house.
And he welcomed people of all types:
imperfect people, sinners...
He welcomed all into God's house.
I am a teacher
and I often teach my students that part of respect
is learning to trust one another
and that you should be able to trust your neighbor.
Trust takes a long time to build
and it seems like it's all too easy to destroy.
We have a certain segment of our population
that has discovered fear as a commodity
which is marketed regularly to the general public.
I'm Amy Kelly from the committee on worship and ministry.
And I think we probably have some visitors here today
who'd like to tell us who you are
and where you're from so we can greet you.
Hi, friends, my name is Ali Mutar.
My meeting is an Old Chatham Friends meeting in New York.
But I'm starting my PhD here at Princeton,
so I'll be here for 5~7 years.
It's fine.
I'm quite excited to...
We might claim you for a while.
Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly.
Many people who think they've got Quakerism figured out...
and then visit a typical Quaker meeting
in the south or the Midwest or the Pacific Northwest
are shocked to find essentially a Protestant service;
a pastor, choire, hymns, sermon, virtually no silence,
a pulpit up front and pews facing forward,
and some cases stained glass windows
and steeples on the church buildings and wonder
"Where did this come from?".
It's all traced back to revivals that
spread through the South and the Midwest after the Civil War:
Methodist Holiness revivals, Wesleyan theology.
And many Quakers, especially young Quakers,
wanting to break out of the Quietest period.
♪ There's version that you're running out
♪ my way
There is less of an emphasis on silent worship as part of it.
We have done it on occasion,
but we do not have it in every service
like some Friends churches do.
♪ Amazing grace ♪
♪ How sweet the sound ♪
One of the ways that the Evangelical movement has probably
affected us as Evangelical Friends is,
in some ways, impacting music.
In more recent years,
with a desire to reach out to new people,
to bring people into the faith,
music is a huge part of that.
And so more contemporary styles of music is more appealing,
especially to some of the younger ones
and that's the ones that we want to reach.
♪ You hold my world in Your hands ♪
♪ I believe ♪
♪ You're my portion ♪
♪ You're more than enough for me ♪
♪ Jesus, You're all I need ♪
The roots of this Quaker diversity also lie in the 19th century,
when American friends responded in different ways
to movements and the larger American religious culture.
The first of those splits took place in the 1820s,
when American Quaker is divided
into Orthodox and Hicksite groups.
At the center of this separation was
a Quaker minister from Long Island named Elias Hicks,
who became a lightning rod for Quaker controversy
when he argued that there were parts of the Bible
that were not truly inspired.
Probably no aspect of their history is
a source of greater pride for quakers
than their central role in the crusade against slavery.
Lucretia Coffin was born on Nantucket to a Quaker family.
She would become known as the most famous woman in America
for her role as an abolitionist and as a leader
in the struggle for women's rights.
By the time she married James mott and moved to Philadelphia,
she was poised for activism.
In 1833, Mott joined forces with other women,
black as well as white,
Quaker and non Quaker,
in organizing the Philadelphia Female Anti-Slavery Society.
It would become the strongest such organization in the nation.
Lucretia was the driving force behind the construction
of the imposing Pennsylvania Hall in Philadelphia.
It was intended to be the center
of abolitionist activity in the country.
Angelina and Sarah Grimke, Quaker converts,
were among the few southern women abolitionists.
They were the daughters of a prominent Charleston,
South Carolina's slave-owning family.
Both left the South for Philadelphia,
where they could speak out against slavery.
On April 17, 1838,
3 days after the opening of Pennsylvania Hall,
Angelina Grimke took the rostrum
before a full integrated audience of both sexes.
As a southerner,
I feel it is my duty to stand up here tonight
and bear testimony against slavery.
I have seen it.
I know it has horrors that can never be described.
I was brought up under its wing.
Our witness for many years
it's demoralizing influence
and its destructiveness to human happiness.
The next day,
an incensed mob set the 3-story structure of fire.
The Quaker journalist and poet John Greenleaf Whittier,
editor of the abolitionist journal "The Freedman",
emerged from the burning building after
rescuing manuscripts from his office.
Lucretia Mott spoke out against
slavery in a variety of venues within Quaker meetings,
but also in public.
And she and others women were willing to speak before mixed,
sometimes called "promiscuous" audiences,
meaning men and women.
And this scandalized a number of people in that era in Philadelphia.
And so they were criticized sometimes less as abolitionist
and more for women being public speakers.
And so she becomes involved and
what was seen as the first women's rights meeting
the Seneca Falls Convention of July 1848.
And 4 of the 5 people
who called and organized that meeting were Quakers.
Films, phonograph records,
and cartoons depicted the suffragists
as unsexed women trying to ape men.
♪ I've been reading in the paper of a very funny land
♪ It's the land where the women were the trousers
♪ where women is the boss and poor old man in secondhand
In the 19th and 20th centuries,
many attempts were made to continue silencing women.
Suffragists campaigned and struggled successively for 72 years
before winning the right to vote in 1920.
Susan B. Anthony was jailed
for publicly casting a vote along with men.
Alice Paul was arrested and thrown in prison.
She was on a hunger strike when she was force-fed
with a tube through her nostrils.
Alice Paul was 8th generation Quaker in this country,
and she was very familiar with their lack of respect for authority.
Alice Paul arrives in Washington at the end of 1912,
and she has a mandate from the National American
Woman Suffrage Association to organize a parade.
It will be the day before Woodrow Wilson is inaugurated,
and it attracts as many as 200 000 onlookers,
which in Washington men was unheard of
and even large by today's standards.
About 4 blocks into the parade, the crowds break through,
and they spill into the path of the parade.
Most of them are men.
They've been drinking.
They hurt all insults at the women.
They spit at them, they tear at their clothing.
The women were under orders not to fight back.
This was nonviolent resistance.
The police show very little interest in bringing order.
They turn their backs on the parade, they're laughing.
Now you would think Alice Paul would had been devastated,
but no.
She saw that this near-riot
on the front pages of newspapers
across the America was a better story
than her parade would have been,
and she was in fact a public relations genius.
She was truly a leader and nonviolent resistance.
The first people ever to pick at the White House,
the first social protest parade in Washington...
She really blazed a trail.
And I think she was to suffrage
what Martin Luther king was to civil rights.
♪ Hurrah, hurrah.
♪ Hurrah for the suffragettes.
I am so moved when I think about women
standing in front of the White House,
demanding their right to vote,
even in the midst of a war.
And it was a very real risk and women went to jail.
But I wouldn't have just been able to vote
if that weren't the case,
if she didn't do the hunger strikes that she had done in jail and
the way that she pulled other women in
and had a big vision for what was actually possible
and took tremendous risk herself.
And I stand on her shoulders.
PNC was claiming to be a green bank
and they also are a bank with Quaker roots.
And a lot of Quaker institutions still had their money in PNC
because of that historic connection.
And so it seemed to us to be a way
to tackle these big issues of justice and climate change
by going after one target and having a sustained campaign.
And so we worked on, for 5 years,
getting PNC to withdraw that financing
from mountaintop removal coal mining.
Quaker organizations come to Friends Fiduciary
as a group to incorporate Quaker values
in the financial stewardship of their assets.
So we manage about 350,000,000 in assets for
Quaker meetings, churches and schools across the country.
Because Earth Quaker Action Team
primarily involves Quakers,
there's a certain affinity
between Earth Quaker Action Team and
Friends Fiduciary because we serve Quaker organizations.
Friends Fiduciary co-filed a shareholder proposal
with Boston Common Asset Management,
one of our partners,
asking for the company
in this particular case
to report on their greenhouse gas emissions and
looking at climate risk in their financing portfolios, generally.
We did civil disobedience and a big growth came in 2013,
when we staged 15 actions on one day.
And the last action of the day was 7 people getting arrested.
We are here...
And we will fight.
We need it every community a group of angelic troublemakers.
Our power is in our ability to make things unworkable.
We then continue to grow geographically,
and on December 6th of 2014,
we were able to do 31 actions
in 13 states in the District of Columbia.
So I think part of what happened was
they saw we were not going away.
We were growing.
we were becoming more bold.
The time that we visited the CE, Bill Demcheck, at his house,
he actually came out and talked to our people for an hour,
and that was assigned to me that we were really making an impact.
So it took 5 years, it took lots and lots of work,
it took lots and lots of people.
And we did it, they got out.
They were very strategic and as I said, thoughtful.
We are using Quaker worship as part of what we do
and that there's a lot of safety in that.
There's a lot of experience of community which
everyone I know is hungry for and especially young people.
I think especially young people are wanting community,
aren't necessarily looking for that
on Sunday mornings at a church,
but want to be able to act powerfully in the world
and have a spiritual rootedness to that.
John Woolman was an early Quaker abolitionist who
wrote a journal, which has been continuously in print
since it was published in 1775.
And it's inspired many people to follow their consciences.
He has the ability to,
I think, put himself in other people's shoes,
this active imagination to put himself in the shoes of Indians
who are no longer living on the land that they used to live in.
He puts himself in the shoes of slaves,
slaves with Quaker masters.
He puts himself in the shoes of Quaker slave owners
and realizes that they have pressures toward holding on to slaves
and that just freeing your slaves is not a simple decision.
In John Woolman's part of New Jersey, West Jersey,
one in every 20 people was a slave.
Let's imagine that John Woolman comes to visit
someone who holds others in human bondage.
And so he arrives,
and the plantation owner says,
"Welcome, let me get you something to drink".
So I bring out my tea and my finest silver,
and I say, "Will you have some tea?".
And he says, "Well, actually I don't drink from silver vessels".
"Well, why would that be?".
"Well, do you know where silver is mined?".
"It's mined in Caribbean, it's mined in Brazil,
and it's not mined by free labor".
We talk about slavery, how it is opposed to,
all religious principles,
how it is, ...
not just bad for the slaves,
but bad for the slave holders and for their children.
Finally as John Woolman is preparing to leave,
he reaches into his pocket,
pulls out some coins and says,
"Oh, well, I understand you don't compensate
your servants for their labor."
"Well, I think people should be paid for what they've done,
especially for me.
So I hope you'll give this money to your slaves".
We have 2 sides, we have the spiritual, slightly mystical side
and we have our action in the world side.
And John Woolman is a great example of these 2 sides,
balancing each other and informing each other
that what we think inwardly in how we experience the divine
then affects how we act in the world.
Friends began to experience opposition from those
who were watching Quakers free their slaves,
which was against the law.
And so friends had to find ways of getting around the laws
and eventually were very involved
with the Underground Railroad.
There was a large network of
anti-slavery activists in Indiana.
Levi Coffin became a quick order,
a very important cog in the movement.
There was a bounty hunter who came
looking for his slaves here in Newport
and was pacing outside the house
and was very frustrated
because he could follow the
trail of fugitive slaves to Levi Coffin's house,
but then the trail suddenly went cold.
And he said, "Well, there's an underground railroad here
and this man, Levi Coffin,  is the president of it."
In response, Levi Coffin said,
he would accept the office of president.
And he would accept any office including conductor,
engineer, or brakeman in the Underground Railroad.
The important thing was to  serve
the cause of oppressed humanity,
the way that Jesus his Lord had told them to do.
Many friends were leaders as abolitionists,
but at that time they were not seen as heroes.
At that time, they were seen as people
who were going against the norm
and that was challenging the Religious Society of Friends
to stretch and to transform and to change.
Quakers were the first to
have the religious society as a whole say
it was not appropriate to enslave people of African descent.
But they were clear when they did this in 1776
that they wanted to have segregation themselves.
So Quakers did delay integration
of the majority of Quaker schools.
There were a few Quaker schools
that admitted some African Americans in the 1930s.
But the majority of them didn't until after the 1950s,
after the 1954 decision.
The Supreme Court's decision in Brown v. Board of Education
meant that all public schools were ordered to desegregate.
Yet African American applicants
to many Quaker schools and colleges
still reported that they were treated differently.
The main reason,
actually around the hesitation for membership and
for having desegregated schools was,
there was fear of race-mixing.
♪ You don't have to ride Jim Crow
♪ No, you don't have to ride Jim Crow
♪ On June the third, the high court said
♪ When you ride in the state,  Jim Crow is dead
♪ You don't have to ride Jim Crow
My activism did not spring for my being gay
or for that manner for my being black.
Rather it is rooted fundamentally
in my Quaker upbringing
and the values that were instilled in me
by my grandparents who raised me.
Those values are based
on the concept of a single human family
and the belief that all members of that family are equal.
Bayard Rustin was born into a Quaker family.
His grandmother was a Quaker.
He was raised by his grandparents
and he remained a Quaker all his life.
His grandmother's influence was enormous.
She was not just a Quaker, but she was also
an activist around questions of race and race relations.
So she was one of the charter members of the NAACP
and joining in 1910.
So that she had this dual tradition that I think he was heir to
and marks his career through his entire life.
Rustin was enormously important in the civil rights movement
and particularly in the 40s, 50s through most of the 60s.
And he is instrumental in introducing a number of different
tactics, strategies, philosophies into the movement.
Generally, he's the one that's given credit
for introducing King to nonviolent direct action.
♪ I'm on my way
♪ And I won't turn back
♪ And I'm on my way
♪ I'm on my way
I now bring to you
the executive director
of the committee for the March on Washington,
the man who organized this whole thing, Mr. Bayard Rustin.
Ladies and gentlemen,
at 5 o'clock today...
the leaders whom you have heard
will go to President Kennedy
to carry the demands of this revolution.
It is now time for you to act.
What do you say?
Rustin's pacifist Quaker beliefs also
led him to become a conscientious objector during World War II.
He worked for the American Friends Service Committee,
the humanitarian organization founded by Quakers in 1917.
I am a Quaker,
and as everyone knows Quakers for 300 years
have on conscientious grounds,
being against participating in war.
I was sentenced to 3 years in federal prison
because I could not religiously
and conscientiously accept killing my fellow man.
The American Friend Service Committee was founded
as a means of providing young Quaker men
an alternative to military service.
Byard Rustin was an employee
of the American Friend Service Committee in the 50s,
helped author the famous pamphlet "Speak Truth to Power"
about the Korean War and nuclear proliferation
and militarism in American Society.
First editions of that famous pamphlet
did not include his name because he was an openly gay person,
and even the American Friend Service Committee
in the 1950s couldn't grapple with that.
It was not until 2013 that Rustin was finally given his due
when he posthumously received
the Medal of Freedom from President Obama.
Herbert Hoover is seen by many of the period
as this upright, upstanding, virtuous
emblem of what quakerism should be.
♪ Once I build a railroad
♪ made it run
♪ made it race against time
Herbert Hoover was elected
president on the Republican ticket in 1929,
the year of the massive stock market crash.
In the face of mounting unemployment and food schiscity,
he insisted that it would be morally wrong
for the Federal Government to provide the help
that neighbors should be giving one another.
As a result, he owned the depression
and every cluster of shacks around the country,
of which there were many became known as Hoovervills.
all the time
♪ Say, don't you remember,  I'm your pal
♪ Brother, can you spare a dime?
Richard Nixon was a California Quaker,
and what that means is that California Quakerism
tends to be more evangelically inflected
than other kinds of Quakerism.
So Nixon growing up wouldn't have had silent worship.
He wouldn't have had a minister
and so becoming an adult,
Nixon viewed himself firmly in a Quaker tradition
that came from his mother.
But it was also an evangelical tradition.
Nixon and Hoover are friends.
And I do think there's probably a connection
between them both being Quakers
in terms of their close affinity to each other.
So Nixon is sort of a protégé
of this old lion at the Republican Party.
Herbert Hoover,
when he had been the first Quaker president,
had gone to Washington meeting.
Nixon doesn't do that
because it's an unprogram meeting
and that means that anybody can speak.
They can't have him in an unprogram meeting
because he's just going to be attacked
the entire time over the Vietnam War.
Nixon decides that he's going to
hold a series of worship services
inside the White House in the east room,
going to invite a number of different
religious leaders in order to lead them.
It's by invitation only
and a lot of the people who receive an invitation
also happen to be Republican donors or people
that the White House particularly wants to impress
by getting them close to the president.
Others saw him as a hypocrite.
They referred to him as "The Bombing Quaker".
And I thought that was a terrible...
juxtaposition of words
because how could you associate that with Quakerism?
I had become familiar with the Quaker peace testimony,
that it was... Philadelphia yearly meaning had copies of it
that were readily available.
So every day, no matter where we were,
I had to get to a mailbox first thing in the morning
so I could get it in the mail.
I mean, all this talk about Quaker heritage,
and I wanted to remind him that
what he was doing was certainly not very Quakerly.
So in terms of protesters, Nixon is obviously very upset
by the fact that people are protesting ham,
protesting his actions in Vietnam.
He's particularly upset by the fact that
Quakers are doing so and so their various remarks
Nixon makes to his staff and to others
that indicate Nixon doesn't see them as real Quakers.
Nixon makes the argument, for instance,
that people who are Quakers
protesting outside the White House
must all have recently joined Quakerism
in order to, like, dodge the draft.
There is an very honored history within Quakerism
of participating, even creating, generating,
designing non-violent direct action campaigns
that enable masses of people to participate
and get something done despite the opposition.
The "Yacht Phoenix" has self-ordained mercy ship manned
by a crew of 7 determined American pacifists.
Its mission?
To bring medical supplies to the
North Vietnamese port of Hai Phong despite Red Cross warnings
and without State Department clearance.
I felt like I had no choice but to offer myself,
because I was compelled by the spirit.
I think a key decision
that friends need to make is whether
to pay attention to the people who look us over
and that would include young people,
because this is a time of spiritual searching.
So what is special about a Quaker school,
as opposed to a non-Quaker school  or a public school?
What do we do differently here?
- Alley.  - We believe in spices.
The spices, yes. the spices.
So what are the spices?
Florence.
The 'S' stands for simplicity.
S-I-M-P-L-I-C-I-T-Y.
- 'P' stands for peace.   - Peace.
The 'I' is sometimes a little tough, Beatrice?
I think it stands for integrity.
What does integrity mean?
That's a really tough question
because it's a nice big, tough word.
Alana, do you...
You were doing the right thing even when nobody's looking.
That is a wonderful answer.
When you open up the dialogue
and you allow students to really grapple with issues
and really talk about it in a way that is meaningful and tolerant,
then they feel like they have a stake in the matter.
The future of Quakerism may rest on new kinds of outreach.
We live in the age of the internet,
so Quakers are knit together in a really new way
because we're Quakers have split
over the years from the 17th century.
We've become evangelical Quakers
and liberal Quakers and conservative Quakers.
And mostly in the past couple of centuries,
we haven't interacted between those branches at all.
But now that we're on the internet,
there might be something exciting that's about to happen.
And there might be a revival of Quakerism
coming up in the next 20 years.
♪ And he wore plain clothes
♪ And he was strong
♪ And there were 60,000 Quakers
♪ When he was done
Most Quakers view the combined experience of silence
and communion with God's light
to be at the heart of the faith.
Both early Friends as well as modern day Quakers
have always been guided by the light.
James Tyrell, the Quaker artist,
experiments and plays with color as its affected by light.
Some Friends experience it as divine radiance.
I attend this meeting house, Chestnut Hill,
and I love the meditative peaceful space
of just laying down and surrendering.
I love the exposure to the elements in the sky,
and the wind and the clouds
and the things that you can't control
or that are greater than ourselves
and that's framed by this rectangle in the roof.
All of what we're doing is spiritual.
It is about that of God in each of us.
It's about the respect we have for each other.
It's about the responsibility we each carry.
And so it's been so exciting to me to see people,
whether they become ultimately Quaker or not,
finding what does it mean to sit in a gathered group in silence?
What does it mean to speak coming out of that silence,
to speak that deep, capital T, truth?
And so I've seen these, like, people blossoming
because it's a way of saying, "Yes, I don't have to have
my faith over here and my activism over here".
They can actually be one.