it's very important to go on an inner
journey but it's as possible to get lost
on an inner journey as it is in an
outward journey in the world so what we
try to do in the courage to teach
retreats is to create a form of
community in which people can go inward
they can go inward through reflecting on
poetry or stories from some of the great
spiritual traditions that raise critical
questions about our lives they can go
inward in silence they can go inward
through journaling walks in the woods
all the simple ways that human beings
have of becoming more reflective of
taking time to simply listen to their
hearts to let the world get quiet and
hear what they can hear from in here
but but it's very important to come out
of that solitude into a community that's
willing to hear what you think you have
learned and not to judge it not to tell
you whether it's right or wrong but to
hear it in a way that allows you to hear
yourself more deeply one of the things
that I always say to retreat groups is
that we have a strange conceit in
Western culture which is that just
because we've said something we think we
know what we've said and the most
important things we say especially under
these reflective conditions are often
things that that come from what I call
the inner teacher I don't alone call it
that I'm a Quaker and in the Quaker
tradition there's a 400 year history of
affirming that every human being has an
inner teacher when the inner teacher
speaks through my mouth it may take me
years to understand what I've just said
and what its implications are for my
life but that process is going to be
greatly helped along by having a
community of people who are willing to
hear me into speech who are who are
willing to let me say whatever is truly
on my heart and
mind not to judge it not to fix it not
to advise me not to set me straight but
simply to let me hear myself at a deeper
level and that's a very special form of
community I think it's a community that
most people have hardly any experience
with if at all because it's a community
that that engages you but it doesn't
engage you with fixes or saves it
engages you with first of all listening
and then with honest open questions what
did you mean when you said that can you
say more about that this is what you're
talking about connected in some way to
other areas of your life this is of the
kind of community we try to create in
our retreat groups and I think it's a
kind of community that teachers find
astonishing in its in its positive
consequences for their lives