our educational system is in huge crisis
what troubles me is that the way we're
defining that crisis is it's a fiscal
crisis or it's a structural crisis or
it's a crisis of kids who can't pass
tests
we're not defining it the way I think we
need to define it which which is a
crisis in our failure to support the
people doing the work at the deepest
levels of their lives teaching is very
demanding work teaching requires a heart
as well as a mind teaching requires a
capacity to create hospitable space for
young people who are fearful who are
anxious about life and about what
they're being asked to learn and if we
can't support the people who are doing
that demanding work by extending to them
hospitality by extending to them the
things that help enlarge and deepen
their hearts as well as the information
they need to teach and the techniques
they need to teach then I think we've
got a real crisis on our hands and
indeed we do