now the courage to teach is on many many
levels I think the one that comes most
quickly to me that's been with me for a
long time has to do with the fact that
our educational system is so riddled
with fear if fear is what we use to
quote motivate young children to learn
as if we didn't know that young children
are natural learners that young children
are curious these young children want to
probe everything hang around with a four
or five year old for a while and what do
you get question after question after
question after question why how what who
and yet somehow we get into them into
schools and after a few years we think
we have to use fear to motivate them to
learn now you sit down and do this or
you're gonna flunk the test you're gonna
fall behind Johnny or Susie you're not
gonna get to go to college you're not
going to have a good life we use fear as
an inducement and of course all we
induce is paralysis paralysis of the
spirit paralysis of the mind so in the
middle of all that fear it takes courage
to teach because because the teacher has
to penetrate the students fears too the
teacher has to create an alternative
reality to the one being created by the
school system or the world around the
child and that takes a lot of courage
that means you're swimming upstream
you're going across the grain and it
takes guts to do that
the other reason it it takes courage to
teach our and other reason is that
teachers have their own fears they fear
that they can't they fear that that
they're holding something so precious in
their hands the life of this child or
and or the subject that they're teaching
which most of us who teach take very
seriously that they can't do justice to
these treasures and and so you teach
with trembling knees you're always
feeling inadequate to the task and it
takes courage to come back day after day
after day to that to them to that sense
that there's a gap between what
you're able to do and the potential
that's in these kids and how you want
them to look at the world through the
lens of your discipline or your subject
so those are some of the reasons it
takes courage to teach additionally it
takes courage to deal with
administrators who don't understand what
teaching is really about it takes
courage to deal with politicians who
claim to be putting forth policies that
are in the best interests of our
children but which aren't policies that
in fact Arce merely in the best
interests of the politicians promoting
them ways of manipulating public opinion
to get elected to office I call it evil
when the claim is that this is for the
sake of the children and in fact it's
for the sake of getting some grown-ups
elected to office and giving them lots
of perks while the children are getting
crushed in the process I think that's a
reasonable description of social evil
and I think it's what's going on in our
society it takes courage to stand with
integrity in the midst of a situation
like that