I think the hardest part about being a teacher
is to see the potential that is
in the young people you're working with.
And to see all of the things that
get in the way of them fulfilling that potential.
I think the hardest part of being a teacher
is to look at human lives being sorted or wasted,
human lives being diminished.
Sometimes by what's going on in the community
or by what's going on in the family,
but also by what's going on in school.
If you think for a while about these teachers
who are now being told by every politician in the country,
your job is to get these kids
to pass this test at a higher score,
so that your job will be secure
and your school will get money.
Well, I think we know the outcome of that.
The outcome is banality,
the outcome is trivialization of the work
and the outcome is the crushing of lives of kids.
What our teachers going to do
under those circumstances?
They're going to spend a lot of time
getting the kids ready for the tests,
not dealing with those issues
in the children's lives.
That wort their development that build barriers to
their growth as human beings.
It takes a rare and courageous teacher
under those circumstances to say:
"No, no, I'm not going to teach to the test,
I'm going to teach these children what they need to know,
to be full human beings in a very difficult world".