In many ways the kind of community
we're trying to create in the courage to teach
is a community that is devoted to
encouraging self-reflection.
Because the human self,
what Thomas Merton called true Self,
I don't mean the ego,
I don't mean the fancy designs we have for,
how we ought to look or how we ought to succeed
or how much money we ought to be making
or how we ought to be liked.
I mean that  that true self that is
the core of every person,
that's the gift we have to give.
And we are trying to create a form of community
that invites self-reflection in order to
put people in fuller possession of that gift.
Thomas Merton said it well, he said,
we are called to give our hearts to the world,
but first we have to have our hearts
in our own possession.
You can't give what you don't have.
And so this is a two-year process to
recover the gift you arrived here with at birth.
But may well have lost in the intervening time.
Now the house of that are many and various.
One thing I love that we do a lot of
is we put what we call a third thing
in the middle of the communal circle.
The third thing is a poem or a teaching story
from one of the great spiritual traditions,
Taoism, Hasidic, Judaism, the New Testament, Sufi stories.
We use a range of materials.
We put a third thing
in the center of the circle carefully chosen,
because that third thing carries a theme or an issue
that we're wanting people to be self-reflective about.
And the facilitator's task is
through a dialogical process of questioning,
is to help that community of teachers
weave a tapestry of understanding about
where their lives intersect that third thing.
I give you a concrete example.
We use a poem by May Sarton.
... is a great poet, called 'Now I become myself'.
It's fifteen or twenty lines long
and I don't have it all committed to memory,
but I give you the first four lines:
"Now I become myself,
it's taken time, many years and places.
I have been dissolved and shaken,
worn other people's faces..."
You don't have to put much more than
those few lines in the center of the circle
and ask some questions about how those
lines intersect the lives of the people sitting there.
To evoke the most amazing range of reflections
about how long it takes to become the self
that you were when you got here,
that you lost somewhere along the line,
about those dissolving and shaking moments in life
where everything falls apart and
it seems like all is lost.
But out of that re-emerges true self,
about wearing other people's faces,
sometimes for better,
sometimes for worse when you're young,
sometimes it's great to have a good face to wear,
when you don't yet know your own,
the face of an admired teacher or a parent or friend.
But as we grow older, wearing our own faces,
becomes the most important piece of work we have to do.
But we put a third thing in the center of the circle,
the task is not to ask as one might do in a lit crit class,
what it may certain mean by that
or how did that relate to mace art in lives,
all of that is irrelevant here.
The task is to allow that third thing
to invite the voice of the inner teacher
in the people in the circle
to come forth and to speak about things
that it might not otherwise be able to speak about.
It's very interesting that
you can say things about that poem,
which are really things about you,
without ever talking about yourself directly.
But we all know that that's who we're talking about.
Poems and stories are like Rorsa's tests.
and when people respond to them.
They're saying a great deal about themselves.
And in this form of community
where nobody's gonna jump on you for what you said
or nobody's gonna try to save you, fix you
or set you straight.
You have a chance to hear yourself at a new level.
And you go to bed that night thinking,
"Oh, my goodness,  I just realized something
that I need to work with here,
something about who I am,
something about my woundedness
or something about my passion that
the inner teacher is trying to tell me.
And now I need to pay attention...
Journaling, of course is
a method of an approach to inner reflection
that has been used in a lot of
different traditions and schools of thought.
And I think what it does is to allow you
to have a conversation with yourself.
I think external conversation is enormously valuable,
I'm constantly learning from other people.
And a lot of that learning from other people
goes on in the courage to teach groups.
But there is finally a conversation
we need to have with ourselves:
"Why did I do that?
Why did I say that?
What did I mean when I said that?
Am I going to do it differently tomorrow?".
These are things I have to ask myself and
I have to listen to answers that I don't necessarily know.
I know that some people who teach journaling
encourage a process of imaginative reflection
in which you have a dialogue between
two different parts of yourself.
And people start doing that
thinking well this is kind of silly
because I'm in charge of everything
that's being said here why a dialogue.
But after a very little while
they're discovering that the partner in that dialogue
is saying things that they didn't know, they had to say.
So there's live learning going on from within ourselves.
I think one of the most
exciting experiences in life is
to understand that I am a walking community
of many voices of many intersecting
lives and forces, past present and future.
I'm a one person pluralism,
I'm not a monolith,
I don't speak even to myself with one voice.
And to understand that what I've got in there is
a city, at least a neighborhood that
needs to have some good block meetings,
some good dialogues to sort itself out.
And to listen to the diversity of voices that
any human being contains.
That's a great thing and
a very exciting part of the human journey.