First word, part one.
What sound?
[Student] E.
What word?
[Student] Pure.
Good, next word, what sound?
[Student] E.
What word?
Gerard?
Are you with us?
What word?
[Student] School.
Okay, part two.
What sound?
(bell ringing)
(students laughing)
♪ First bell rings I hate that sound ♪
♪ Back of the class with my head down ♪
♪ Got a test, all kinds of stress ♪
♪ Can't take home another F ♪
♪ Sometimes I need to stop ♪
♪ And breathe ♪
(girls laughing)
Alright, time to ring the bell.
(bell rings)
Okay, partner up everybody.
My name is Ling Busche, I'm a seventh grade counselor
at Marina Middle School.
You gotta go to the end of the line.
Nice try, Deshaun.
We're one of the larger middle schools.
We have a student population of about
nine hundred.
Line is going pretty smooth today.
There is a great divide
in terms of student population.
Guys, let's go inside.
You've got the honors classes that
have the highest performing students,
no behavior problems.
Then you have the general ed classes, which are a mix,
but contain students who have the lowest test scores.
I virtually get no behavioral referrals for the
honors classes.
All of the disciplinary referrals are coming out of
the general ed classes.
(children chatting)
We do haves students who seem well-served,
who are successful, who perform well and
within our very same campus, we have a group of students who
are completely disconnected and disengaged.
There is a significant number of our students
that don't see school as a place for them.
I always say it by saying,
"they don't do school."
Diego.
One disruptive kid can take away any learning
that goes on in the class.
(students laughing)
So other kids wanna misbehave because they think
everybody's misbehaving.
Shut up, you cricket.
(students laughing)
Fat mama.
Ooh.
When the class is crazy, and throwing pencils,
it messes up my concentration fully.
So the thing I do is I just sit in my chair and do nothing.
Chris?
Turn around, get on task.
I have sent out and suspended from my classroom
more students than I have in a long time.
You're gonna get me in trouble.
I just find the behavior to be completely off the wall
and unacceptable, not just toward me, but toward each other.
A lot of kids might not feel that
school is always relevant to them.
School is structured for a certain type of kid,
and maybe they're not that type of kid.
It reaches a point where they don't feel like they're heard.
Number ten to forty,
even.
This was the assignment yesterday.
[Ling] When you visit Mister Ehnle's class,
it feels very chaotic in there.
What is going on with you two?
Get out a piece of paper.
Science.
[Ling] There's sort of this sense of
nonstop entertainment,
and whatever's happening in the lesson
often becomes secondary.
Do not misspell the word amphibian.
Anyways,
I forgot what I was saying.
[Ling] Their engagement is tied to
the drama that's happening in the yard,
what's happening on Facebook,
and they are consumed by it and so it just continues on
in the classroom.
[Student] Stop kicking me.
Did you see what this freaking whale just did?
(students laughing)
That's your backpack?
Yep.
Excuse me?
It's my backpack.
[Student] That's Connor's backpack.
Jeanette.
Jeanette, leave the room.
I'd go back out with Edwin.
[Ehnle] Slope is M.
We're going to take a Y value.
[Student] He be hanging out with Tiara a lot
on the bus, he always be sitting with her.
I know, but they broke up.
Well, she broke up with him.
Excuse me, if I continue
to hear talking, one or both of you are gonna find
a new seat.
[Student] Ugh.
No, that's not ugh.
It's yes, Mister Ehnle, then you get on task.
With that many bodies in a classroom,
when somebody needs to be moved off to a corner,
there are no corners, 'cause there's already somebody there.
I've given up.
I just put 'em next to each other.
'Cause I'd rather have them talking and yelling and
carrying on next to each other than across the room.
Think about it.
Lately,
we would all learn much more if nobody really was talking
or getting distracted.
We would all, like, have our grades up,
we would all be good kids and everything.
I know we're good kids, we're smart,
but sometimes,
I guess we're too lazy to show it.
Okay, you have one minute to finish your spelling
and then you need to get a purple book
that's right in front of you.
You stupid bitch.
That's why nobody likes your ugly ass.
No one likes you.
[Miss Illes] Gerardo, keep going, you're doing it.
[Ling] Gerardo does get angry sometimes
and seek out a challenge with his teachers.
He basically shows up and
produces very little work.
It has really brought him down
in terms of his academic performance.
I'm not the only one that fools around.
[Gerardo] Yeah you are.
No, I'm not.
Shut up, we're gonna get fucking zeroes.
If I get frustrated, I get hot and then after,
I get cold, all the heat goes away.
I just finished all my work.
It's not a good feeling that I have.
Could you stop writing on my work?
Please?
Middle school boys have trouble
sitting still for long periods of time and focusing
at their desks.
This really doesn't work for them in general,
but that's the way school looks.
That's how it's structured.
Open your books, please, to lesson 15.
First word, what word?
I already did it.
[Mister Ehnle] Omar?
Omar, when the teacher says read the first word,
that's what you do.
I read the first word.
[Mister Ehnle] On cue.
Mister Ehnle's class is a jungle.
Everyday somebody gets sent out.
Always it's wild in there, everybody's out of their seat,
just around.
It makes it hard for me to focus 'cause I get distracted.
It makes it hard to learn.
[Mister Ehnle] So let's reconvene.
Malik?
Go sit over there by Jacqueline.
[Jacqueline] No.
I really fear for these kids who
don't put forth the effort.
They don't try.
They don't persevere.
Next word.
Next word, what sound?
What word?
Good, next word.
What sound?
How can you put together a relationship,
how can you stay at a job when it's not fun
if you have not learned to persevere?
What is it that you?
I'm not reading.
You're not gonna help yourself be successful
when you're behaving like this.
Omar?
What?
This is not the way to help yourself be successful.
[Omar Voiceover] I do like learning new stuff,
but if they're teaching it in a difficult way
that I don't understand, then I'm just gonna stop trying.
You know what?
I don't wanna hear any arguing.
I know I could do better.
If I just turned in my homework.
Tonight's homework for science is twelve dash three.
(girls laughing)
Jacqueline, go sit in the back.
Ugh.
No, it's not smacking your lips, it's go sit in the back.
Mister Ehnle does disrespect me.
He has an island on his head.
He dresses weird.
He has huge
glasses.
And he screams a lot.
No, you're next to Gerardo.
No, I'm next to Lesly.
You're wasting not only your time,
the sad part is you're wasting others' time.
I wanna know what the text is.
When are you gonna have it again?
Jacqueline, if you are having a conversation,
it will end or you will be out of the classroom.
Why do you always send me out of the classroom?
Huh?
Because you do so much talking.
He's assuming that I'm always the one that's
starting the problems.
It makes me feel mad.
[Mister Ehnle]
Jacqueline, get your stuff
and go see Nick.
[Ling Busche] When the teachers have tried
things in the classroom, then the student comes down
with the referral.
[Jacqueline] When we get kicked out,
we go down to the office.
I'm always the one that he sends out.
It always feels bad.
Sometimes, they get pigeonholed because of,
you know, previous patterns of behavior.
I think that they
all feel like the underdogs.
No one's rooting for them.
(somber music)
Gerardo, when you get sent down,
nine times out of ten it's because of something like,
which seems small, like an argument.
She's like you have a history of doing stuff
and I said but I'm not doing what I used to back,
back in sixth grade or nothing.
A lot of the students that come in and out of the office,
ironically, sometimes it feels like they
want to come to the counseling office,
which is a little bit of a dilemma because
they're outside of the classroom more.
And it's, like, not fair.
If it all boils down to it, you're messing yourself up
because.
But if I'm not doing nothing,
how am I messing myself up?
How am I, how am I,
how am I the one that's putting myself into this
when I'm not doing nothing?
You're missing your test,
so now it's gonna be kind of a hassle to get you
to make up that test.
It all adds up.
But I didn't do anything.
[Ling] Nothing?
Nothing.
When you're in the moment
and you're in front of the class, things get
heated,
they become, you know, the problem becomes escalated.
I want my mom to come and talk some sense into that lady.
[Ling] Okay, well she can be part of that, too.
[Gerardo] I swear, she just.
We have a consultant that
came in recently, and she
actually described our school as apartheid-land,
which, I was at first a little bit offended by, but
after thinking about it, I understood what she meant.
Because she saw who was coming in and out of
the counseling office.
I don't want to see you in here with another referral today,
Gerardo.
Alright.
[Ling] Get it together.
It's our Latino and African American kids
who are underachieving, who don't feel like they're part of
the school and
we have to address that, we have to make those kids
part of the school and we have to allow those students
the opportunities and, in fact, get them to achieve
at a higher level.
Hey, Chris, why don't you just come into my office
and I'm gonna clear off that little table for you?
Something that would benefit all of the kids had to happen
across
all of the students.
So when one of our therapists talked about the idea
of going into the classroom to teach
meditative strategies which would
reduce conflict,
increase focus, you know, we were like, that's perfect.
Moises?
[Moises] Yes.
Why are you out of class, buddy?
I went to get groceries.
[Principal] We are suspending
at a rate higher than any other
middle school in this city.
And I know that that has to stop.
(somber music)
What we'd like to do is create a sense of
this is a community, and we're not just gonna push you out.
We're gonna help teach you about how to do this
and do it well.
So we're gonna look and see where you are at in the process,
how many times this has happened with you.
[Omar] It's only happened once.
She says there was a sixth grade incident, though, so.
So one of the reasons that we embraced bringing in
mindfulness into the classroom was to say if we could create
a bright light within the community, where adults and
children can see that, hey, something is really working
to make this community more inclusive and for everybody,
if we can start creating those spots around
Marina Middle School, then others will see it and start to
adopt that
empathetic and that attitude of saying that the school
is gonna meet more of those needs.
(quiet string music)
My name is Megan Cowan,
and I am here from an organization called Mindful Schools.
We go into classrooms
and teach something called mindfulness.
I'm gonna be visiting your classroom
twice a week for just 20,
maybe 30 minutes
and one of the things that we'll be doing in mindfulness,
which is gonna be a little bit unusual,
and I think weird for some of you, is we're gonna,
there are gonna be periods of time that are totally silent.
[Student] So what, are we gonna be meditating?
So let's raise your hand if you wanna have a question.
The biggest misconception is that mindfulness is
spiritual or religious.
Although it can be traced back to
very traditional practices,
it can be used in a secular way to address issues
in society today.
What we're gonna try right now is just what I call
mindful posture.
If you're slouching or leaning, just lift off your chair
momentarily for a few,
we're gonna do this for about two minutes, maybe.
And take your hands and decide to put them
either on your desk or in your lap.
[Student] You said put them on your desk?
Or in your lap.
And then notice if anything in your body is moving,
like if your leg is bouncing or your foot's moving,
or your fingers are moving.
I think of mindfulness as a tool or a skill.
Society and
our culture is training us to
not be focused, so technology is causing us to jump from
one thing to the next constantly, all the time.
And when we're asked or required to focus on something,
our brain, actually, is not prepared to do that.
It's not trained to do that.
So I think on a very practical level,
it's just creating more focus in our lives.
And try to let everything become still.
Ugh.
[Megan] And notice that this is uncomfortable.
[Student] It's not
uncomfortable.
[Megan] And if you feel the need to talk.
It really teaches about
increasing impulse control
so that we get more choice around our actions.
Okay, now relax.
Keep your attention with me.
(students laughing)
[Gerardo] I feel horrible.
[Megan] Yeah, tell me why you didn't like it.
It was like, it was alright.
Then later, I couldn't feel my body and
it felt kinda weird on my legs, so,
like if I got shot or something, I don't know.
[Megan] Can I have everybody's eyes up here?
Thank you.
[Mister Ehnle] Chris?
[Chris] Yes, ma'am?
(students laughing)
Before I leave,
before I leave, I wanna tell you guys about
the science behind mindfulness.
Science shows that mindfulness actually affects our brain.
And when we use mindfulness,
(girls laughing)
you know what, you guys?
We're gonna have to figure out some way to make this work
since I'm gonna be here 15 times.
[Student] 15 times?
I did find myself having expectations that I
deserved some more time before they would choose to be
deliberately disruptive or before you check out,
but I think apathy is part of being a teenager,
so I wasn't surprised.
So what I wanna ask is that
there's a certain level of attention in the class
that shows that you are at least willing to listen
for awhile.
Chris?
So, if you want this level of attention,
you gotta make stuff entertaining
'cause kids over here are hyperactive.
Mindfulness
actually is
training you to be comfortable
when you're not being entertained.
'Cause you will not be entertained 24 hours a day
of your whole life.
Hang on.
When Megan came in, I thought, oh man,
we're that bad they gotta bring a t.v. show about us?
I'm not sure how our class was chosen,
but.
[Ling] The kids ask why mindfulness was brought to
their classrooms because it's not being offered in
other classrooms, and I think they know the reason why,
generally, that the classes are a little bit crazy at times.
It's hard to go down that road when they're so used to
going down the other road
which is a road of chaos and disorder.
(hip hop music)
If they cooperate,
and they, like, pay attention, they would change but
because I know some of the kids won't,
I don't know about the class.
(girls screaming)
[Female Student] Did they get in?
Did they get in?
Lesly,
(speaks in foreign language)
she doesn't pay attention in class.
She doesn't do homework like she should.
It's not my fault.
because you didn't tell me where it is!
Before, she always paid attention,
turned in her work
the teachers never complained.
Not all of my family members
got to finish middle school and high school,
and I want to show them that I can do
what they could have done, and I want to prove to them that
I can go to college and show them that
I'm getting a good career and changing my life.
(speaking in foreign language)
We/re going to pray.
We always talk to her.
So, try to limit conversation in class.
The class is for studying, paying attention.
friendships are for when you leave school.
I tell you the things you should do, but you don't listen.
I go to church and pray for you to open your mind
do good in school, do things right
for you not to do bad things.
When I see that she's not doing well
I tell her there's no telephone,
there's no television
there's no shopping, going to the stores
or if you want something, I tell her there's nothing
because if you don't behave
I'm not going to give you a prize.
If you don't put forth effort
who is going to give you a living so you can live?
Nobody, right?
Sometimes I tell her, you've got everything
that a person like me doesn't have in their own country.
And you don't know how to take advantage of it.
That makes me sad. For me, as a mother
that's the saddest thing, that so many young
people that are the children of Latino parents
kids who've been born in this country
and they don't finish school.
(bell rings)
When the sound of the bell is completely gone for you,
raise your hand.
When Megan first came to the class,
we really didn't know what was going on.
We're usually loud and we yell across the room and
we just get up from our seats and like,
crack jokes and stuff.
We were just trying not to be our normal selves in class
when she came in, but it was kinda hard.
Can you turn this way?
Just go ahead and turn your whole chair
and face that way.
And go ahead and scoot up like,
a foot and a half.
Thanks, but facing that way.
Like, just turn your chair
so you're exactly facing that way.
Thanks.
[Male Student] I am facing that way.
Okay, but do you understand why I'm asking?
Yes.
Thank you.
So put your hand on your belly
and everybody take one deep breath
that only you can hear.
Let's try it again.
And now,
take five gentle breaths,
(students laughing)
noticing if you feel it in your belly.
You have your hand on your belly, it gives you another
way to feel that you actually are breathing.
Our breathing is responsive to our emotions,
so it's a nice way to stay connected with your experience,
is to be watching or noticing your breathing.
And then take three breaths, noticing if you feel it
in your chest.
When Megan first came
to teach the first mindfulness class,
I was like get outta here.
I don't wanna do this, you know?
I was trying to look like a good kid in the beginning, too,
but then it was fun throwing pencils and stuff, you know?
Not listening to teachers is always fun,
but it's not the thing to do.
We're gonna do a challenge,
and the challenge is to do mindful breathing for a minute.
So everybody in your mindful posture.
(girls laughing)
What?
Chair.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
It's not no.
No, no, no, no, no.
I don't want to go over there.
I didn't ask if you wanted to.
Yes, you did.
[Megan] So, I know there's some distraction,
but we're just gonna continue.
We're gonna do a minute of mindful breathing
starting now.
Chris, can you put your hand in?
I'm gonna walk by.
Chris?
(speaks in foreign language)
Thank you.
For some of you, there was something about that experience
that may have felt pleasant,
or positive.
Hey, guys?
What's your name again?
Rusty Shackleford.
[Megan] So Matt Rusty Shackleford,
(students laughing)
can you help me out by just having your attention up here?
Alright.
[Megan] Okay.
So can I hear from four or five people
one word that describes what that was like for you?
Calm.
Calm?
And would you describe that as a pleasant or
unpleasant experience?
Pleasant.
Thank you for sharing.
Monica, go outside.
You do too much, for real.
I know you don't like expectations.
I do, but I don't like yours.
It's not like it's hard to reach them,
it's just like they wanna act like they don't really care
about nothing.
But I know that they do care.
They're trying to act like they're tough.
They try to act like, oh, I'm better than this, you know?
When they're really not better than that.
Raise your hand if something about
a minute of mindful breathing
was unpleasant.
I'm not used to breathing so quiet.
I've lived in San Francisco for a long time,
so you always hear like cars and stuff.
And it wasn't noisy, so.
Okay, so you're used to the noise in San Francisco.
So we're gonna end right now with the bell.
Ssh.
(bell rings)
We did do mindful breathing,
and so I accomplished what the intention was,
but it didn't feel like the class really got it.
And it took 35 minutes.
You just really want to find a way to reach them and
you're not, and so I don't know,
I don't know where to go next with it.
Hey, there's Malik.
They go around the corner.
Steven Hopkins goes to After School with me.
That's how we stay out of trouble.
In the beginning, I had like, all As.
And during the middle I just started not wanting to
do my work and stuff.
I would just go to school and not even do anything,
just not do my work, go have fun.
[Dad] What do you want to do?
Yeah, nothing.
[Dad] That's good.
Kind of fast though.
Does it?
Yeah.
When he comes home, I always ask him are you okay?
How was school, what did you did?
Anything change, anything wrong?
So I try to get at least an idea of what happens
during the day for him.
If I just put him on the side and never talk to him,
or don't care about what he does,
then that's different.
Yeah.
Gerardo is in trouble now.
For the past maybe, I would say a year, year and a half,
we're having really hard issues with him.
Tardiness.
Attendance.
Behavior.
The friends that he hands with and the things that he does.
It's like if you're doing good, they give you pluses.
If you're fooling around or not in your seat or something,
they give you circles.
How many pluses you got today?
Altogether or in the group.
Eight.
In your group, in table ten?
Eight good?
Yeah.
How many bad?
Seven.
(laughs)
Are we doing equal here?
Are we doing minus or plus?
Come on.
And I was getting referrals sometimes,
five referrals a day, and the thing with him,
he likes to talk back.
One time they called me at work and says
you have to come pick up Gerardo right now.
We cannot keep him in school no more.
And I'm like, it's 11 in the morning.
He says well, you need to come pick him up.
They just want you to leave the premise and don't come back.
That is pretty bad.
But I was doing good, though.
I understand, but for how long?
I graduated from Marina Middle School.
I was exactly like Gerardo.
I was very smart.
I was actually the student of the month for
six months.
I had
honor roll for about six months.
And then everything went down sour, too.
I started hanging with the wrong crowd,
answering back, not doing homework,
until eventually I got kicked out of school.
Sometimes I fool around in class.
Oh, that I know, you don't have to tell me.
Why do you think you sit in the front?
'Cause you're special?
'Cause I love my teacher.
No, you don't.
Alright.
No, it's not alright.
Don't just tell me alright just to tell me to be quiet,
I'm trying to make a point here.
It would not be fair for me to go to work on time
and have everybody else be late when I'm on time every time.
I know what my job is, I don't need someone to come tell me
you need to do your job.
Yeah.
There's little things out there that I regret I done
and I was, believe, I coulda go back, I woulda change it.
That's the thing that I'm trying to teach him,
I says look at my mirror, look where I am.
Look what I gone through.
I been doing dishes, I been doing janitorial work,
I been doing all kind of jobs.
I've been selling fruits in the street,
so to me, that's nothing new, but for him,
that he has the chance and the opportunity
to be somebody here,
he just doesn't take advantage of it,
I think it's a waste of time.
I don't think the school,
but he needs to come up with better choices, though.
Right?
Yeah.
(bell rings)
[Student] Sound like we're in Hong Kong.
Can I have your attention?
So the way things went on Monday,
it's not gonna work for mindfulness, so I need to find out
who really does not want to be here for mindfulness.
I'm gonna need each of you that are raising your hand
that you don't want to be here, to tell me why.
So you don't want to be here because?
It's boring?
It's boring and it's stupid.
[Megan] Do you ever find other things in your life
boring or stupid?
No.
[Megan] No, never?
So this is the only thing?
So you definitely wanna go?
Yeah.
[Megan] Okay.
There are a few kids
who make the rest of the class particularly challenging.
If there were five of them that weren't in there,
then the majority of them actually would be trying
and would be participating.
Diego, come here.
And stand up.
Just come all the way over here.
Okay, they're just gonna head outside with you guys.
And we're gonna have the class without you.
Thank you.
It's our philosophy as a program that all students
are present in the class, even if they are the
disruptive ones, because we believe that they are the ones
that might even gain the most benefit.
But, right now what I'm seeing is
there's a handful of kids that are causing
so much disruption, that it's at the expense of the other
30 kids in the class.
30 kids are waiting for the class to settle down.
If you're participating in the class,
please turn your chairs this way.
Everybody's eyes up here.
Chris?
It really did strike me when I looked around at the end
and there was one boy
just looking at me so intently, and then I looked around
and I realized, well, a good half of the class
is just waiting for the rest of the class to
get it together.
Some of the people that are ready and willing to do it
are not gonna feel comfortable unless the rest of the class
is settled in.
[Student] So why don't you ask all the kids in here
if they're feeling comfortable right now?
That's a conversation that I've been trying to have.
So raise your hand when the sound of the bell is gone.
(bell rings)
(alarm rings)
Oh, we're supposed to be going to lunch.
It's like hitting a brick wall.
I just am frustrated and kind of hopeless.
The defiance is so deliberate and
I don't know if I can work with that
in this large of a group.
So, I sat down with Mister Braxton and Miss Busche to ask
how I should respond to this class.
The problem that I'm
meeting with these kids in particular is that
four kids are being deliberately disruptive
at the expense of 30 other students.
We're a public school.
We take everybody where they're at and we do
the best job we can with them and the idea that
30 kids are waiting for five kids.
[Megan] Yeah.
Or that somehow these kids are the victims
or they're not getting something at the expense of others,
that's a paradigm I prefer not to set up,
that some get and some don't
and that we sacrifice five so that others do.
We should give
the same thing to everybody.
It may not come in the same way, though.
And I'm okay with that.
Let's take this one day at a time.
And today we'll take those four out for the class.
You'll have some time with them and then maybe
you and I can touch base before I leave today
just to hear how that conversation went.
And then
reintegrating them when that class comes back together
as a whole, it's not foreign to four kids in the class.
[Megan] Right.
(somber music)
I had a parent teacher conference and it was bad,
'cause the teachers were talking bad about me.
Not a lick of work.
Nothing turned in,
math or science.
I always do this on the overhead projector.
By not doing homework,
she thinks that's the way she can get back at the teacher.
Everyday, she should be able to bring a paper home
that looks like this.
This is what we did in math class today.
She got behind in math and
reading and writing, also,
because the teacher sent her to the
office.
[Mister Ehnle] We talked about it for three days in a row.
When I went to school,
homework means like two, three hours and then
I have my free time.
Me, Lyn and Lesly Martinez worked on it.
In America, it's like, boring for them.
Getting a diploma is like, whatever.
What is that going to get?
You really shouldn't even think that's bad.
You're gonna be so proud of yourself.
The Principal said that if she gets one more thing,
she'll have to change the school.
But I don't want her to get out of Marina.
I like the school.
She could do very well
if she focused and really decided
I'm gonna be a great student.
I think I would have to change my whole attitude
and start doing my work
and my homework.
All of my homework.
[Mister Ehnle] I think it's really up to you.
I think you have the resources and it just takes
a decision on your part to do your part.
I hope to pass.
I would feel kind of sad.
If I don't pass, then I don't get to go on with my friends
and move on.
Doesn't make any sense, to come to school
for the full year
if at the end, you don't graduate.
I waste my time.
[Jacqueline] I did think that was a wake up call.
I walked out thinking start doing good,
stop getting referrals and start doing my homework
and classwork.
When I wake up in the morning,
and it's the day that we're teaching at this school,
I have a mixture of mild dread
and also some determination of what can I do today?
These classes are
on my mind all the time.
When I feel like I'm not reaching them,
that's not acceptable so I wanna get creative
and figure out how to reach 'em.
(contemplative music)
(bell rings)
Okay.
I'm gonna have you guys start
leading mindfulness.
[Gerardo] Please let your eyes close.
(bell rings)
I wasn't planning to give it a try today in class but,
I kinda did.
Okay, thank you.
Alright, you guys.
What do you think is your biggest influence in your life?
Everybody started paying attention
and it was different from the other classes.
[Megan] Lesly?
Dad.
[Megan] Dad.
Jacqueline?
My sister.
[Megan] Okay, so we've got dad, sister.
Gerardo?
[Gerardo] Art.
Art.
Would you be surprised if I told you
the biggest influence in your life is your mind?
And when we practice mindfulness, you're strengthening
your mind to have the influence on your life
that you want it to have.
And when we practice mindful breathing,
we're developing the strength of our mind
to have influence on us.
It was hard to sit still
and to not move my hands or anything.
It was just like, okay, I just need to calm down and
tell myself to stop moving to see if this works or not.
One way that we can create influence in our life
with our mind is by having thoughts on purpose,
rather than thoughts on accident.
So go ahead and get back into a mindful position.
I'm gonna say a phrase.
So the first thing I want you to repeat,
silently in your mind, is
I wish
for myself to be happy.
And then try the wish, I wish for myself to be healthy.
And now create a wish in your mind that is
specific to yourself,
whether it's something you want to accomplish,
a quality that you want to have,
something you want to do.
I wish for myself,
you fill in the blank.
It just helps you relax and forget about everything else.
Is anyone willing to say
what they wished for themselves?
Yes, what was your wish for yourself?
An easier life.
[Megan] Thank you.
Gerardo?
To do better in school.
[Megan] Great.
In his class.
[Megan] Thank you.
You wish to do better in school,
particularly Mister Ehnle's class.
Yeah.
I want to move to Alaska.
[Megan] You wish to move to Alaska?
Yeah.
Okay, great, thank you.
Raise your hand if this was the first time that you
had thoughts on purpose about your happiness.
Okay.
I want you, three times today, wish yourself happiness.
Okay?
But your challenge is to remember to do it.
And I want to express my deep appreciation
for your participation today.
Today's class definitely does make me feel more hopeful
that we're gonna get somewhere in this class.
That room really shifted today and I felt like
the students really participated in a way that
was helpful to them, as in each individual,
but also as a classroom.
Okay, thanks.
Thank you, Mister Ehnle.
I have thoughts about the mindfulness program.
I'm perfectly willing to participate and
I hope it helps students
in learning and effectively using the opportunity
that is their middle school experience.
(soft music)
[Students] Six, seven, eight.
Good morning, again.
[Student] Hi.
Hi.
Good morning.
How are you?
[Student] Good.
We're gonna go into mindful listening.
I encourage you to have an open mind this morning,
while we try something that you
probably haven't done before.
(bell rings)
Keeping your attention on sound, listen to the sounds
outside the room.
(children chatting)
And then focus on the sounds inside of you.
At first, well, I thought she was like a voodoo person,
'cause of what she was wearing.
You guys got really mindful.
Can you identify how you felt
listening to the sounds outside?
I was a little impatient.
[Megan] A little impatient?
Yeah.
[Megan] Yeah, why?
'Cause I'm used to moving and chatting a lot.
[Megan] You're used to moving and chatting,
exactly.
So try to be mindful of sounds,
outside, inside, inside yourself.
And I will see you on Monday.
Thank you again, you guys, that was great.
(students applauding)
Mindfulness program is,
it's alright.
It's okay.
I think it'll only help certain kids
that really is interested in it.
Some kids just come to school because
they just feel like socializing.
And some of the other kids,
they're more interested in school and the programs
that happen at the school.
(jazz music)
Omar, he was really getting a lot of trouble in school.
He had straight Fs.
Oh, he'll say one D, but to me, that's still straight Fs.
Had very bad discipline problems,
a discipline problem with not doing what the teacher says.
And just a problem kid.
How you doing?
How was your day?
[Omar] Good.
(jazz music)
How's your asthma?
[Omar] Alright.
Me and my husband, we thought it would be best
for him to stay with us, as I had just retired.
There's some cookies.
What you got, progress report?
Yeah.
He brings home a progress report,
that's one of the things that he's required to bring home,
to me, everyday,
and that's been every day since he's been going to Marina.
But, what about Miss Illes?
There's nothing for Miss Illes.
Everyday I've been asking you for.
Omar can be quite challenging when he's defiant.
Quite challenging.
I forget.
But that's not acceptable, right?
Alright.
So when are you gonna start remembering?
I need to know what she says, I know what you tell me.
[Omar Voiceover] She has expectations from me.
She just wants me to do good in school.
I need you to put down what she says about you.
[Omar Voiceover] She's pushing me to do well.
Sometimes I don't really listen to her.
I just didn't do it this morning.
I think you need to start doing more.
I don't really care,
I don't have nothing to say to her.
I just want to see some improvement from you, you know?
The best thing about raising Omar is
since I'm retired now,
I get to spend a lot of time with him,
whereas before, I was working, trying to make ends meet,
rushing with dinner.
Just didn't have that time to sit
and really appreciate him being there.
But now, I love it.
Just being there for him.
He's a great person, he has a big heart.
But, he has a lot of disappointment that keeps surfacing.
[Omar] Why?
'Cause I'm gonna win.
Alright, let's play Horse, though.
He needs to learn how to
handle those disappointments or negativity,
so he doesn't feel like he's lost the battle.
Must be butter on the ball.
It's no butter,
there's probably butter on your fingers.
With practice,
mindfulness would work for him
but it would really be hard to get through that curtain
of anger,
getting hold of it
for him to grasp it.
We're gonna get through that,
and mindfulness is going to help.
(bell rings)
Today I brought you something.
What I brought is something that we can eat.
What I brought that we can eat is raisins.
(students laughing)
Okay, so somebody tell me your three reactions.
Yeah?
My first reaction, I was excited.
Second one,
I was like,
okay.
The excitement kinda went away.
Then you said raisins.
I don't eat raisins.
(group laughing)
I'm gonna hand them out.
So just hold it right now, don't eat 'em yet.
So what I'd like you to do is
open your mouth.
Ssh, we're gonna do this quietly.
And take a whole minute to chew it.
[Student] A whole minute?
[Megan] And what I want you to pay attention to
is how your raisin changes.
[Student] It's so sour.
We want to bring mindfulness
into our entire experience, not just
sitting still with our eyes closed.
Mindful eating gives us a chance to experiment with
being extra present in something that we do everyday.
I want you to notice the flavor, how it changes.
The texture, how it changes.
Every moment of our day includes our senses
to some extent, so it's a great way to bring them
all together in that one moment.
But your challenge is, the next time that you are
eating something that you like, I want you to be mindful
of it so that you can experience it
differently than you have in the past.
Okay?
Thank you, you guys.
Have a great rest of your week.
I'll see you next week.
[Lunchlady] It's $5.50.
You guys ready?
Come on.
Come here.
(Spanish music)
I love my friends.
I can tell them anything.
That's the only reason why I come to school,
to come see my friends.
I don't like being in class
'cause it's boring.
I think mindfulness is more boring than class.
Okay, wait, wait, stop.
Okay, go.
One, one, two, three, one, two, three.
At school, everybody trying to see
how far they can go,
that including Jacqueline.
Move the damn chairs, you two.
(girls laughing)
stand right there.
[Jacqueline] I don't tell my parents everything.
Parents take everything too seriously.
She have to be a better person if she don't want to
struggle when she gets 20, 22.
I think it's going to get into her
at some point.
[Megan] Raise your hand if you have somebody in your life
who you have difficulty with but it's somebody
that you care about a lot
or you love.
And bring to mind this person who you care about,
but maybe there's some challenge with.
Repeat silently,
I wish for you to be happy.
Ever since my parents broke up, I really
didn't care if I was angry or not.
My teachers and everything, like I really didn't care
if they were frustrated with me or anything.
[Megan] I wish for you to be safe.
I wish for you to be safe.
Gerardo has a lot of anger towards me.
I think we have up and downs like everybody.
Sometimes we get along good, we have fun together,
we spend time together.
And sometimes we just don't get along.
Sometimes I think it's because I'm not living with his dad
and it's hard for him to understand that we're
not together anymore.
Find a wish on your own that's meaningful
regarding this person, and you make the wish.
You choose the wish.
Sometimes mom, she yells at me.
The whole place just feels all
like a pot of water that's cooking, you know?
It's all heated.
Sometimes you can run away form it,
sometimes you really can't.
Sometimes you just gotta like, be there,
and you gotta burn, the little pot thing.
[Megan] Let your attention rest in your body,
just noticing how your body feels and how your mind feels.
I want Gerardo to graduate, have a degree.
I know that he can do it,
but right now it's tough timing, it's really hard for him
to focus in school.
But I want him to be somebody in life.
[Megan] That was great,
but I'm really curious if anyone is willing to share
what that was like.
The room felt still, but when I looked at each
individual student, I didn't know what was going on
for them and they're not being really forthcoming
and sharing.
Can I have a show of hands
if anybody thought that it was helpful
or that you learned something?
Or you realized something?
By the end, hopefully they do have a tool that they can
depend on or
draw upon in
moments of need.
("Ready or Not" by The Fugees)
This morning I used mindfulness 'cause mom,
she was yelling at me 'cause I didn't get up in the morning.
And I was just mad.
I was just gonna lock the door and like,
go back to sleep and not go to school today
but then I,
I just chilled for a little bit, I used mindfulness
real quick and it made me feel more calm.
It kind of woke me up, too.
And I came to school.
♪ Gonna find you ♪
♪ And take it slowly ♪
♪ Ready or not, here I come ♪
♪ You can't hide ♪
Good morning.
So, what I want to try this time,
is while you're doing mindful breathing,
I'm gonna deliberately gonna make a little bit of noise.
And using the anchor words
breathing in
and breathing out will help you stay
focused on your breathing even when there's some
distraction or chaos.
(bell rings)
Breathing in, breathing out.
(door slams)
I wasn't surprised in the beginning when things got quiet
people would like, make fart noises and stuff.
But later on,
like maybe like a month later,
things got better.
Things were actually silent when she rang the bell.
And now when she rings the bell, we could be like,
yelling and stuff, and fighting, but we still know
when that bell rings,
that we stop.
(soft music)
Go by the court, Alex.
I haven't talked about mindfulness with my friends.
I talked about it with my family.
I have one brother.
I woulda had another brother, but he died.
I learned how to play basketball from him.
My brother was twenty
two.
So dude, he said he gonna come?
[Mother] No, he want us to come and get him.
Is he gonna come to concert with us?
After his brother died, he changed in school,
his grades went down.
His behavior was kind of nonchalant,
like he didn't really care about too much anything.
And when he got a little older,
that's when you start trying to get in trouble and stuff,
huh?
Yeah.
This is my brother.
He died
five years ago.
I was asking a lot of people if they knew who did it.
Did you?
Yeah.
Some people said yes, some people said no.
Not like I could do something about it, though.
Yeah.
After he died, then a couple other people that you
knew and loved, died too, and so it was,
you start really acting out.
This is my other friend, Gene.
This is the one that got shot in the back of the neck
and ran all the way to his granny house
and died on her floor.
That was in the beginning of the school year.
You miss him?
Yeah.
I do, too.
Yeah?
Yeah.
We used to play over there when we were little.
What was over there?
Just open field.
Was it bigger?
And the tree was so shady.
Did he get killed like right there at the gate?
And somebody had came up and shot him.
Too much death and you get too depressed,
it's almost like a war zone sometimes
out here.
Vinnie used to heckle balloons over there?
Yeah, balloons, teddy bears.
Then what happened?
They put this gate up because at first the gate
wasn't there.
I'm trying to focus on school and sports,
that's basically it.
And hopefully if I keep on playing sports,
that could probably get me out of here.
I could take my family out of Richmond.
We'd just move somewhere.
Yeah, they grew up right here
just like I grew up on this block.
They all dead.
(bell rings)
Alright, can I get somebody to lead today?
Do you want to, Omar?
Omar was participating today.
I mean, he participates in a way that's also
making a little bit of trouble.
He has a certain role
and he's kind of determined to play the role
and participate.
And he seems to be managing that.
Just very elegant.
So hold on, what do you want to say?
Get in a mindful posture.
[Megan] Ebony.
Get up.
[Megan] Oh, you have to be kind, though.
Say it in a nice way.
Ebony, can you please sit up?
Thank you.
[Megan] Thank you.
(students laughing)
(bell rings)
Now look down, and listen to the bell, okay?
Keep your eyes closed.
How do you feel right now?
Relaxed.
Relaxed?
Anything else?
[Ling] I think Omar's reaching a point where he's taking
mindfulness seriously.
Do you like being in front of a group?
Yeah, it's alright.
It's cool.
He's really reflective, he thinks about
what happens, he's able to look at both sides.
Alright.
Go ahead, ring it.
(bell rings)
Mindfulness kind of did surprise me.
I didn't think I was ever gonna use it but I did.
Please notice how you're feeling right now.
We were outside in the yard, and then
some girl just made me mad.
She will beat your ass like Ruby.
I just felt like pulling her hair out
dropping to the floor and choke her.
And I used mindfulness to calm down and not do nothing.
(girls laughing)
I like it, 'cause there's consequences for that.
I kind of feel happy 'cause I get to
really think about things and not make a mistake
that I will regret doing later on.
Move over.
When I get angry at other kids at school,
I'm really good at putting them at their spot.
Dirty old goat.
Oh, she didn't hear.
I've seen the sweet side of Jacqueline,
and I sometimes would like her to show it, but
I guess she doesn't really want anyone to see it.
(girls shouting)
You trying to push me?
So if I was gonna write down words for the Jackie
that other people see, what words would I come up with?
Nice.
Mm hmm.
Funny.
They look at me like I'm mean.
Sometimes they see you as mean?
Yes.
That's awful.
[Ling] Jacqueline likes participating in mindfulness.
I think that her
engagement has shifted.
Isn't it interesting that you can be both?
I'm hoping that she starts to gain some perspective
on these incidents that are happening recently with
other girls and getting into fights and all this stuff
and choose a different path for herself.
What's the Jackie on the inside?
Shy.
I don't think doing mindfulness changes me at all.
Do you think anybody knows you're shy?
No.
What about thoughtful?
[Jacqueline Voiceover]
It's boring, but like,
I could use it as a tool if I'm mad or something.
When people see you as mean,
what's that all about?
'Cause I push them around and like
I hit them and stuff like that.
So you kind of act tough.
Is that who you are?
That is a little bit of who you are on the inside?
Okay, let's put that there.
That's really good for you to be honest about that.
A little mean on the inside, too.
Yeah.
You okay with that?
Okay.
Where do you think that comes from?
I don't know.
She does use mindfulness, I don't know why she
doesn't say it, but she does.
She would have problems and I would help her out,
but sometimes she would just use mindfulness
to help herself.
Your battery is fucking low.
(girls laughing)
Good morning.
Can I get everybody to turn your chairs towards the front?
Ring it again to get their attention
(bell rings)
Good morning.
Can you raise your hand if you remembered to use mindfulness
since I saw you on Wednesday?
Okay, that's a lot.
Can you keep your hand up if you're willing to say
when you used it?
Jacqueline.
Thursday.
'Cause there was a problem.
[Megan] And what kind of mindfulness did you use?
Breathing.
[Megan] And why did you decide to use breathing?
'Cause she told me to calm down.
[Megan] So Lesly was with you
and she told you to calm down?
Mm hmm.
[Megan] And did it work or help or change anything?
[Megan] Will you say anything more about it?
There's nothing else to say.
[Megan] Okay.
I know, alright.
When I have problems at school, I really don't talk to my
parents,
not really my mom.
I don't really feel like she can understand me.
I love my parents. I'm happy to have both of them.
I am the only sister, the only daughter.
I feel lonely with the two little brothers I have.
Sometimes I get mad at them.
Stop throwing it over there.
(speaks in foreign language)
The way I deal with getting mad is that I would just
pretend nothing happens and keep it in me,
never let anybody know.
Same thing at school.
Someone makes me cry and no one else knew about it,
I would keep it to myself and pretend nothing happened.
I really have no way to let it out.
It's always, like, loud everywhere I go.
It's never quiet.
Never still.
When we meditate it's always quiet
and I get to listen to different sounds
and
it's really different for me.
My family would get interest and want to learn about
the mindfulness class and what I've learned from it.
(speaks in foreign language)
It's difficult to be patient.
I understand that if she continues with this relaxation program
it will be calmer and relax this environment a bit.
I like that she's taking this program.
So that we can learn something about it through her.
I have art class for second period.
I like to draw, like, if I want to draw something about
San Francisco, I like draw the buildings and stuff.
I like graffiti arts, too.
And one, two...
Not like drawing apples or nothing like that.
I don't really like that.
(hip hop music)
I draw everywhere to make myself more talented in a way.
With doing graffiti, I can see that the anger goes away
and he will ask for time alone
to do that.
If I practice,
I could be a painter like people here.
I could have as much talent as anybody
but I just need to keep at it.
I don't really need to use mindfulness when I draw,
but like, it gives me a little boost to try to help me
concentrate and try to see what I wanna draw.
When I grow up, if I can paint or draw as a side job,
then that would be cool.
And if I could do it as a solid, solid job,
then I would, yeah, I would definitely do that.
This is nice.
I think it's true that I'm in danger of failing
seventh grade.
It doesn't mean that I'm gonna just quit.
It means that I'm gonna try harder to pass.
Mister Ehnle,
I wanted to know if you as a class have ever done
mindfulness without me?
[Student] Yes.
[Student] No.
We have not.
Okay,
I wondered if you had a bell?
The classes that best sustain mindfulness,
the teachers and the students continue to use the bell
even when the program is finished,
so that there's this constant tool in the classroom
to give a reminder of mindfulness and to facilitate
a mindful practice.
(bell rings)
In terms of calming things down, refocusing,
mindfulness was worth the class time.
No doubt about that.
It makes them feel
like thy have more control over themselves
and their behavior and that they aren't simply
victims of external circumstances.
So, now we're going to look at some math.
The volume of a circle,
Pi times radius squared.
Before mindfulness, I would just be like,
not knowing what to do, not paying attention to anything.
And like now, when I need to sit down and do my work,
I just think about it and like, say, you gotta do this,
you know?
What word is this?
[Students] Though.
Though.
I think they feel better about what they're doing.
They have more self-confidence.
They're paying attention better.
That they feel more engaged in the lessons.
Okay, very good.
My personality changed.
'Cause if there was a conflict before,
I would probably be ready to fight.
But now I'm just like, more,
laid back, calm.
[Mister Ehnle] We take a line of symmetry and then.
The role of the teacher has expanded.
The biggest challenge that we have is
changing our systems and structures within these
school buildings so the kids can fit in.
If you go and look at database indicators that help
students learn,
self-reflective behavior is way up on that list,
and that's one of the things that many of our good learners
bring that others don't bring to the school.
And so a program like this that helps teach kids that,
and helps it become a part of the practice within the school
and reinforces that is going to help them.
The whole mural,
it's about how we need more peace in the city.
The best part of making this piece
was working with other people.
I think mindfulness taught me how to calm down,
to try to not put problems in the way of stuff
and choose what I want to think
and choose how I want to feel.
Should I paint over it?
Yeah, and then maybe a layer of white?
Yeah, I know, paint over it.
The other teachers that tell me he can't do good,
all he does is disrupt, you know?
It's like finally somebody's saying that they're
impressed on what I do
and that they're happy that I'm there.
It makes me feel good, makes me feel like
I know I could do it.
Okay, so today is our
last day of mindfulness.
[Student] No!
(students applauding)
Matt?
So, if you have a reaction, or something to say,
I want you to just notice it in yourself.
If you can not control your impulse,
you have to ask yourself, who's in control?
I'm gonna ask you to keep your eyes closed or down.
So I want you to notice the impulse to move your eyes
or move your body.
Or talk.
And really try to contain that so that you are in control,
not something.
Mindfulness doesn't make problems go away.
It's a wrong assumption to think that if you
practice for a long time, then you'll never be angry again,
or you'll never have another problem or no one will
ever be mad at you.
That's not the point at all,
and you can never create that situation.
It's that the way you're meeting your experience changes
to allow more lightness and more happiness
to meet situations.
Just focusing on yourself,
and respecting the people around you,
and we'll listen to the sound of the bell.
(bell rings)
Noticing what distracts you,
and if you can stay focused for two minutes.
I don't know why I get distracted really easily.
Sometimes I get lazy.
I'm gonna have to sit away from my friends
and control myself, do my work and not get lazy.
I did bring something for you today.
Matt, do you want to say something?
[Matt] Yes.
Okay.
[Matt] Is it raisins?
No.
Is it raisin bran?
[Megan] No.
(students laughing)
I will use mindfulness in the future.
I think I kind of take it for granted now.
Megan comes in
and it's like, you get to relax.
Later on,
maybe a year from now or two,
I think I'll use mindfulness more.
They're called pocket hearts.
Whenever you see it or feel it or remember it,
I want it to be something that reminds you that
you have a tool now that you can use
for the rest of your life.
Seeing how my dad works, like, it's stressful.
I think I would want to use it if I was stressed.
It's like something in your backpack,
it's always there and you can just pull it out
and use it.
Once you have your heart,
I want you to think about
at least one thing that you've learned.
I get distracted by many people who are sitting beside me.
They're gonna start teasing me and bothering me
about everything.
I just like going to a private place and saying
all my thoughts inside of me, what I feel.
Nobody is there to look and see anything that I do.
Can anybody say how school would be different
if everybody practiced mindfulness?
Yeah?
No bullying.
[Megan] No bullying, yeah.
Why do you think that would make no bullying happen?
Because many people have been getting hurt by people
picking on them.
[Megan] Yeah, thank you.
It'll make a difference
if the whole world used mindfulness.
A lot of people wouldn't be killed.
It would be less shooting.
Alright everybody, I wish you a happy summer.
And if I don't see you next year, happy eighth grade.
Take care, thank you.
♪ Sometimes I lay under the moon ♪
♪ I thank God I'm breathing ♪
♪ Then I pray don't take me soon ♪
♪ 'Cause I am here for a reason ♪
♪ Sometimes in my tears I drown ♪
♪ But I never let it get me down ♪
♪ So when negativity surrounds ♪
♪ I know someday it will all turn around because ♪
♪ All my life I been waiting for ♪
♪ I been praying for ♪
♪ For the people to say ♪
♪ That we don't wanna fight no more ♪
♪ There'll be no more war ♪
♪ And our children will play ♪
♪ One day ♪
♪ It's not about win or lose ♪
♪ 'Cause we all lose when they feed on the ♪
♪ Souls of the innocent ♪
♪ Blood drenched pavement ♪
♪ Keep on moving though the waters stay raging ♪
♪ In this maze you can lose your way ♪
♪ Your way ♪
♪ It might drive you crazy but don't let it phase you ♪
♪ No way ♪
♪ Sometimes in my tears I drown ♪
♪ But I never let it get me down ♪
♪ So when negativity surrounds ♪
♪ I know someday it'll all turn around because ♪
♪ All my life I been waiting for ♪
♪ I been praying for ♪
♪ For the people to say ♪
♪ That we don't wanna fight no more ♪
♪ There'll be no more war ♪
♪ And our children will play ♪
♪ One day ♪
♪ One this all will change ♪
♪ Treat people the same ♪
♪ Stop with the violence ♪
♪ Stop with the hate ♪
♪ One day we'll all be free and proud to be ♪
♪ Under the same sun singing songs of freedom like ♪
♪ One day ♪
♪ All my life I been waiting for ♪
♪ I been praying for ♪
♪ For the people to say ♪
♪ That we don't wanna fight no more ♪
♪ There'll be no more wars ♪
♪ And our children will play ♪
♪ One day ♪