?????????±????????
It's hard work to think about standing
in the tragic gap, not passively but
in a way that helps something happen there
that's for the common good.
It's hard work to draw deep for those sources
of courage in our own life and to embrace
the fact that we both have courage and
are called to courage.
The question arises where does one find
nourishment and sustenance for that hard work?
And I want to suggest that
the Clearness Committee, or this way of
holding each other on the shoulder,
is one answer to that.
It's not the only answer, but one answer,and an answer that
in my life and in
the lives of a number of people I know
has been a powerful one,
a powerful source of nurture and sustenance.
Let me turn to the schedule now and just walk through
this process before we start digging
into the depths of it. At 9:45,
thereabouts, we're going to sit down
in silence in these spaces
in a small face-to-face circle and the silence will
be broken by the focuse person when he
or she is ready to begin. So right away
our job is to hold a quiet,
centered, focused space without chitchat.
For several hours this morning
we are suspending the normal rules of social
interaction and we're going to do
something very different
for reasons I'll try to explain in a moment.
From 9:45 to 10:00 the focused
person will describe his or her issue
while committee members listen without
interruption. They may stop before 10:00.
They certainly won't go on much
longer than that
and our job during that time is to
listen. They will give us a clear signal
when they are ready to start receiving
questions. And then from
10:00 to 11:30 the rule is questions only.
Committee members may not speak to
the focus person in any way except to ask
brief, honest, open questions. This is
where we're going to do some work this
morning about what is ruled out and
what is ruled in because our behavior during
this time, our verbal behavior and our
nonverbal behavior is very important.
It's the core and the heart of the process.
[Music]
Mirroring can be a very valuable moment
in this process. You've sat and listened
deeply to this person for an hour and
three quarters, hour and a half, and yet
it's also that slippery slope where we
might slide back towards trying to
advise, fix, save, set someone's straight.
And so if you can remember during this
time that you serve this person best by
being a literal mirror, and I will
illustrate what I mean.
If you say to the focus person,
?°When you were asked this question,this is how you
answered."  Amen, I simply invite you
to look at that as the subtext,
the implicit message.
You don't say why you think that's
important. You obviously think it's
important but you don't tell them. Why?
You don't do anything except hold up a
mirror that reminds them of a question
that was asked and an answer that was given.
There's a second kind of mirroring
where you say, "I invite you to look at
three questions and three answers
simultaneously."
You obviously have a theory about why
those hang together in some way
but you are not to say what theory is.
You are simply to mirror that these three
questions were asked and these three
answers were given. And you let the focus
person make of that whatever he or she
wants to make of it.
Constantly the effort here is to
withdraw our desire to shape this
process or to interpret what's going on
or to import our own wisdom and simply
to let the person get a clear bead on
the inner teacher, on their own inner wisdom.
Body language mirroring can be
very valuable. It's even trickier.
It's harder to do.
You have to be a phenomenologist to do it.
Good mirroring would say,"When you were asked about job A,
your voice grew soft and your eyes
were downcast. When you were asked about
job B, your head was erect and your voice
was loud."  You'll notice what I didn't do
there. I didn't say,  "When you were asked
about job A you seemed subdued and
depressed. When you were asked about job
B you seemed enthusiastic and excited.
Don't you think its job B?  Why don't you
go sign up right now?"  The point
being, even though I think I know,
I have no idea what
those downcast eyes and that soft voice really
mean. Quite the contrary it may not be
depression. It may be this is the most
serious possibility I've looked at for
a long time and I'm considering it deeply.
I can't get inside another person and
interpret them. And my job here is to
remember that and to not invade this
person's soul, this person's inner space.
If the focus person invites
mirroring, those are the disciplines we
need to practice and it can be enormously
valuable in that last 15 minutes to
help a person re-gather things that
have come from within herself or himself
and simply have a chance to look at them
again before
the group disbands. With five minutes
left someone is going to say, "We now
invite affirmations and celebrations" and
I'll tell you what I told the
focus persons last night. In the dozens and
dozens, maybe over a hundred by now
Clearness Committees I've done,
I have never known those affirmations and
celebrations to be gratuitous or forced.
They've always been authentic and deeply
felt. It's simply an enormous privilege
to be in the presence of another
person's soul and two hours later you
will feel that privilege and you
will feel the mystery of the human self
and you will want to celebrate the shared
journey and this person who has
given you the gift of a peace of his or
her life
and because we value that gift and this
offering that these three people are
making to us so deeply,
[Music]
we will abide faithfully by the rule of double
confidentiality, which means A) nothing
said by the focused person in this group
or any of the questions asked will
ever be repeated to another soul even if that
person was in the group.
Group members will not talk about this when
it's over. Our job when it's over is to
continue to hold the focus person
in our thoughts and the
light in whatever way you hold people. And secondly, the
second part of double confidentiality
is that none of us is at liberty after the
Clearness Committee to come up to the
person a day later, a week later,
a month later and say, "You remember when
you said this? I had a thought about that."
We hold this sacred space forever,
henceforth and ever more.
We do not later invade the focused person with our fixes,
counsels, and advices.
Focus people have said time and again that
second part of the confidentiality rule
liberated me to do what I needed to
doing here,which is to have the deepest
possible conversation with myself
knowing that it will stop there and if
one of them wants to come to us
and say, "Would you sit and talk with me?"
They're at liberty to do that.
We're not at liberty to approach them.
Your job as members of the committee
this morning is to create a space that
is to be occupied by the focused person
and the focused person alone for two
hours. If you can remember to keep
yourself out of that space,
both in verbal way and in an energetic way,
right now I'm leaning into this space, right?
My energetics are taking me to
the middle of this because I've got a
message I'm trying to convey.
If I'm a member of a committee this morning,
I need to lean back, breathe deep,
not lean in, and simply hold the space for this
person to occupy herself or himself
without me being in there.
This has all kinds of practical implications.
If the focus person starts to cry
I'm likely to do that this morning
because I'm going to be dealing with some stuff
that touches my emotional life pretty deeply.
Members of my committee are not
liberty to comfort me. They're not at
liberty to move into that space
with a Kleenex or a hand on the arm
that says all will be well because
as soom as they do that they have occupied my space
and they have changed this from
my dialog with my inner teacher,
to a social relationship with them in which I now
have to worry about
what they're thinking about my condition and
making them feel like they're good
caregivers. This is exactly what
needs not to happen. This is not your
father's Oldsmobile.
I need a space in which I can sit there
and ask myself what are those tears
really about and maybe some caring
person in the circle will ask that as an
honest, open question.
"Where do you think those tears are coming from?"
That's a fair question£¬ but comforting me or
trying to help me get rid of those tears
or being embarrassed on my behalf
about the tears is not serving me well
in this situation. Always keeping
yourself out of the space, leaning back,
and yet being fully attentive just
intense with your intentionality
being to support me and my inner dialogue.
I may get off a good joke. You're certainly
free to smile gently.
You are not free to join me in raucous laughter. It's been
pointed out to me more than once that
I'm always the first person to laugh at
my jokes and sometimes the only person.
In this setting, you don't join me
in laughter because I need a chance to ask
myself am I using my sense of humor to
blow off an issue that's really kind of
painful to me? I do that sometimes.
This two-hour period is an opportunity
to reflect on that but that opportunity
is taken from me if you join me in
laughter and turn this into a social
occasion. You're holding the space
with a simple intentionality, a simple
focus, a simple attentiveness,
a remembering that it's my inner teacher
that counts. You aren't going like this,
which is inattentive and disrespectful
nor are you leaning in. You are neither
invading nor evading. You are simply
holding me present in intentionality
that I might have a dialogue with
my inner teacher. Now, there's
one thing that in this regard
before I get to the questions
that I talked to the focus people
about last night.
You have been doing something in the 15
minutes we've been together so far
that's helpful to me under these
circumstances.
You've been nodding when you get it.
You've been looking puzzled
when you don't get it. You've been giving me clues
about what I have to say more about
or what I've said enough about. Under these
circumstances that's helpful but in a
Clearness Committee these nonverbal
signals that we give each other are
radically unhelpful because they turn it
back into a conventional social
situation where my job, and I'm
going to a focus person this morning, subtly
becomes persuading you that I'm on the
right track so that I get you going like
this rather than like this, right?
That's hard stuff to break.
It is very hard for you, as members of the committee,
when you hear my problem and I'm
struggling with something not to
look sympathetic and to nod and a smile and
to encourage me but in doing so,
you maybe leading me down the worst goat trail
of my life and depriving me of a chance
to find my own path. How do you deal with
that? Simple. I've said to the focus
people you are at liberty to close your
eyes for the full two hours to
hear those questions with your eyes
closed, to respond to them with your eyes
closed. If that's not comfortable you can
look at the center of the circle
while you hear the questions and answer the
questions or you can look at the ceiling
or out the window.
Members of the committee are to hold
this person and steady attention, but the
focused person is to disengage from us
as much as possible so that
you are really, the focus person is really,
having a conversation with herself or
himself. This is very countercultural.
This is what you call rude
under normal circumstances but in these circumstances
it's the only thing that works and
I will tell you exactly. It came to me in a
Clearness Committee several years ago.
The power of this, for me as a focused
person, the power is that at some point in this
in this process morning I will be
asked a question that will take me to
a place of truth that
I don't talk about. If my eyes are closed
and I have gotten the message inwardly
that this is not about persuading
anybody of anything, of seeking approval
or being worried about disapproval,
I will be sitting there thinking
the only person I have to fool here is
myself and why would I want to do that? I will
therefore be encouraged to answer
honestly. Questions only. Honest, open
questions. I've never found an ironclad
way to generalize about what an honest,
open question is. Here's the closest I
can come. An honest, open question is one
you asked without possibly being able to
sit there and think I know the right
answer or the best answer to this
question and I sure hope you give it to me.
If there's any energy like that in you,
sit on the question. Don't ask it.
An honest, open question is one you
ask without possibly being able
to imagine what the right answer is.
Let me give you a couple of examples. If I
ask, if I'm a member of the committee
and I asked the focus person,
"The situation you just described. How did you
feel about that?"
That's a good honest, open question.
It allows that person to name some emotions but if
I listen to that list of emotions and
I notice that anger is missing and I'm
saying to myself, "Boy, if I'd been
in that situation I would have felt angry"
and then I asked the question, "What about
anger?"
That's not a good honest, open question.
Now that's a level of subtly that's
hard to attend to but
what I've done in effect£¬ given where
that question came from,
is I might as well have said,
"You know if I'd seen there I would have felt angry.
Why didn't you?" That's invasive and you don't want
to do that. You must not do that. I said
to the focus people last night,
"Everybody in this circles is going to be trying very
hard to keep the rules and sometimes
we're going to screw up and
we can forgive each other for that."
I also said to them, "If anything happens in this
circle that does not serve your soul you,
the focused person, are at liberty to say that
doesn't feel like an honest, open
question to me or things are moving too
fast here or I'm being pressed in an
area that I don't want to explore."
If the focused person says that, the person
to whom they say it is not at liberty to
defend herself or himself or
to explain herself or himself because again,
that's to invade the space with your agenda.
"Oh, I said that because you said this and
I thought that and therefore or
please forgive me." Nothing.
Your only option is listen to that,
to sit back, and try to reenter the process
later in a more helpful way.
That's the only option you have.
[Music]
The pacing of the questions is important.
It's not a grilling or a
cross-examination. Let there be spaces
between questions and responses.
The focused person may ask us to slow it
down if it's moving too quickly for him
or her. If you find yourself asking
a question you may well feel a need for a
follow-up question and that's fine, but
if you find yourself about to ask the
third question in a row
before someone else has asked a question, you're
probably getting into trouble.
Take that as a boundary marker and pull back.
Open up that space. Just a final
image or two, there's so many images that
have helped me try to serve other people
well in this process. One of them,
frankly, is the image of sitting
at the bedside of a dying person. I know
that sounds a little odd but there's a
powerful parallel here. I've done that
a time or two and I've learned two things
that I hope to remember.
One is that in this moment I realize, maybe for the
first time in a while,
that I don't have a fix for this problem.
My job is not to fix this person up but it's to bare
witness, to be fully present, to offer
love and compassion in a quiet,
holding way. I'm not to invade because I can't
do anything in there. I can just
hold them in my presence and at the same time
I learned not to evade, that the most
disrespectful thing would be to run from
the room because what I'm looking at is
too problematic or too struggling or
too difficult to want to bear.
I'mg going to keep my eyes on them.
I'mg going to hold them
in my attention because it would be
disrespectful not to. Maybe for some
of us, remembering that this is like
sitting at the bedside of
a dying person, where you neither invade nor evade
could be a helpful image.The image I
always like to close with is
this very simple one,
that for the next two hours we're going to be
doing something that is
very much like holding a small bird in our open hands,
our open minds, our open hearts, and during those two
hours we're going to face at least three
temptations. One is that in the first 15
or 20 or 30 minutes, the hands start to
close around that bird and we want to
pluck the feathers and sort of do this
dissecting thing we do with our minds,
analyze this person to pieces, try to
figure out what the heck is going on
here and why don't they see what I see.
That's the way the mind works and we are
to resist that temptation. Our task is
simply to keep our hands open and
hold the bird. We're not going to do dissecting
with our minds this morning and if we
don't do it with our minds we won't do it
with our mouths. The second temptation
that comes after an hour or two,
and we're past that dissecting thing,
we're not sort of into the mystery of
another life that is being shared at
a deep level and we've come into that
more respectful respectful receptive mode,
is that the hands are going to get weary
and we're going to want to lay this down
for a while. That means the attention
wanders. The intentionality
disappears and I just want to say to us
a bird is a very light thing to hold.
A soul is even lighter. We can do this
for two hours. We have enough upper
body strength to do that for two hours.
All we have to do is pay attention to it.
The third and final temptation comes
toward the end, which is sort of
like this.
Please fly. Show us that you've
solved your problem.
We put all this time and energy into you.
We need to remember that this bird will
fly on its own schedule and that the fruit of
our work this morning, the proof
that we have done this well, is not that the bird
flies but that we can say we faithfully
held for two hours and when the two
hours are over
those hands can withdrawal into the heart
and we can hold that person for a long,
long time to come.
That's all we're asked to do.
To be faithful to the holding,
the holding of the space, where this person can have a
conversation about something important
with him or herself.