Very few people have an experience
like Saul on the road to Damascus where we just get
blown over by the Holy Spirit
and suddenly everything's changed.
So we have to listen for nudges
and leadings and little quiet steps.
So my experience is of feeling small nudges that
feel like they are from God and that I need to pay attention to,
and if I stop and slow down and have others sit with me
to reflect on those nudges,
I can sense whether they're really something
pushing me in a direction I need to go
or is it just a momentary fancy?
Clearness Committees are formed when
a individual, a couple, a group comes to a Quaker body and say,
We are wrestling with this issue
and we want to discern the way forward."
It's important to know how to help
people to do their discernment
because it's not something that
we learn automatically in our society.
It's not always something we learn at home.
So it's a skill that can be learned,
but we have to practice.
The prep work for the committee is
to hold the person in the light
and be prepared for the questions that may come up
and read the writing in advance to be prepared for
holding this person in the committee meeting.
Before the meeting,
I find a grounded place and
I would pray for that person,
or, to use the Quaker saying "hold them in the Light."
And, for me, holding people in the light,
I visually try to see them surrounded by a halo of light.
The first thing I would say is just to let the person talk.
And I find that often,
we don't have a space to be able to talk
about the things that really matter to us,
and so just holding a space where somebody actually
just gets to tell you the whole story
and why it's important to them, is a gift.
So when you serve on a Clearness Committee,
the first piece of that is listening deeply to the person
who's requested a Clearness Committee.
So the first piece is to listen deeply
and not just to listen deeply
to that individual and to their story
but also to listen deeply
for the still small voice that of God in that person,
and how this Spirit might be moving.
We're all listening to the same source,
the same God is speaking to all of us.
So if I'm saying that, like,
there's a leading that is coming from God
that is telling me to do something,
I have no doubt at all that
another friend would be able to, like,
with enough listening, totally hear that.
Asking each other queries is powerful
because it stops us from giving advice.
It's an opportunity for us to ask open and honest questions
of a person who has the wisdom
within themselves to find an answer.
And so, instead of saying,
"Oh, a similar thing happened to me",
or "I know what you should do in this situation",
we sit and listen to what the person is asking
and then we ask questions about
things that they already know but haven't discerned yet.
Questions make the space for the Spirit
to speak and to be listened to,
rather than, like, kind of laying the options on the table, saying
"Select, choose wisely,
here's which one I would choose".
It's really,
that's not what Quaker discernment is supposed to ideally be,
and like, the questions open the door,
I think for just really exciting possibilities.
I always consider them as a gift.
It's a gift of another experience
and so you look at whatever you're thinking about
from that point of view.
It might never have occurred to us or to me,
to look at it in that way,
but hearing someone else
ask a question allows us to broaden how we look,
how we consider what it is we're doing.
So you could say something like,
"When you imagine yourself in 5 years,
and you've taken that job that you're discerning around,
how does that person that you are in 5 years feel?".
Or you could say something open-ended like:
"If the spirit closed that door,
and you weren't offered that job,
how would you feel about that?".
So those kinds of open-ended questions
that helps the individual imagine the various possibilities.
Even though I might have my own desires for them,
I try to acknowledge I have them,
but I just try to keep them from influenceing them and
ask them open-ended questions to really
find out more about them and
what they are asking for clearness for.
And then,  worshiping with them
and praying with them for guidance.