Early on my time with quakers
I learned about this thing called a Clearness Committee.
And it was basically the way it was described to me,
it's like you've got something you need to figure out,
you have a problem you need to solve
or question you need to answer.
You don't necessarily need advice.
You probably know what you need to do,
but you need to clear through all the things that
are interrupting your ability to access what,
in your heart of hearts know you need to do.
so you can then have a clearness committee.
I have a personal prayer.
I am the clay, mold me.
I am the vessel, fill me.
I am the instrument, use me.
But in trying to decide how best to be used,
I need the prayer and support and listening of others.
A Clearness committee is
a small group of friends that gather and
basically ask you tough questions about
what your leading is, what your concern is,
what's happening inside you, what do you feel.
Well, people we regularly have,
what's called a clearness committee for marriage.
We have Clearance Committees about
whether people are actually called to do a ministry
that they're thinking about.
We have clearness for membership.
Are you ready to join the Religious Society of Friends?
A Clearness Committee, I think, in Quaker terms,
very much involves humility.
You are submitting yourself,
generally voluntarily, to an entity that is
a part of your Meeting, your congregation.
A lot of people will convene a Clearance Committee
if they are getting married,
or if they're choosing what college to go to,
or choosing which direction to go in their career,
or that sort of thing.
So that's where we get the name Clearness Committee.
It's about clearness, becoming clear about a decision.
When we call this group together,
we're looking for very specific kinds of people.
We're looking for people who are good at listening
and who don't have a tendency to give advice.
These should be people that are important in your life
and in the life of your community.
But not so close to you that
they're going to be influenced by
your decision one way or the other.
They're not there to provide answers.
They are there to try and help you see clearly
what the situation is, what's happening,
and what you should do about it.
It's a gift of your spiritual community,
saying, "You don't have to struggle alone.
Here are your companions that can work with you
and go on this part of your journey with you",
which is, to me, phenomenal in this day and age.
That we could be so blessed that our community says,
"You don't have to do this alone.
We will help."
The prep work for a Clearness Committee is that
the clerk will find a place in time
and put together the committee,
and then the person who is the focus person of
the committee will write a page or two in advance.
And so you start off by
actually describing the situation.
Like, really sitting down, writing it out so that
everybody has access to it and you can say,
"Okay, this is what's going on,
and this is why it's confusing to me.
These are what I perceive
my options to be in this situation.
What am I missing?".
The steps involved in the actual Clearness Committee
are to come together and for the person who is
asking for the Clearness Committee
to state what it is that they want clarity on.
So they state their problem or decision point.
Even though it's been passed out beforehand,
I say in my own words,
"This is the situation as I understand it".
Then the committee should ask clarifying questions
that are really just about facts.
Like, "Did you mean you're moving to
Georgia in the U.S or Georgia in Asia?".
That kind of thing.
And then after this time of questioning,
we sit and we wait.
And I've been in Clearness Committees where
sitting and waiting lasted for 20 minutes,
and I've been in Clearness Committees where
sitting and waiting lasted for 3 hours.
So usually people will just listen
and hold this space together,
and ask the Spirit to bring to them clarity.
The committee starts listening together
and asking deeper spiritual questions.
Do you feel that God is calling you to do this?
How do you see your life evolving
if you follow this path?
if you turn away from this opportunity?
So the questions that a Clearness Committee
asks are all going to be questions that are open ended.
And that lead to greater self-reflection,
and to a deeper prayer and to a more imaginative
engagement with the problem or question.
At that point,
the committee's role is to step back and listen and
let the focus person for the clearness process really
respond to those questions at a deep
heart mind and spirit level.
So out of that time, a lot of times people will
share things that they noticed.
Maybe they'll share,
"I noticed your eyes really light up
when you talked about this idea",
or "I noticed a change in your body posture
when you're talking about this decision".
But my experience in this is that
when you've got this group of people
gathered to listen around this issue,
each person is going to hear
a little piece of God's voice, of away forward.
A lot of times, the person themselves will
start feeling that clarity in themselves and
will be able to name it to some degree
and to be able to say,
"Yes, when you shared that,
I really felt like that rang true",
or "That felt right within my body or my spirit".
I've come into a Clearness Committee
with a preconceived notion of what's going to happen,
and it gets blown out of the water every single time.
It's kind of hilarious that way.
I've been on Clearness Committees where the group
found that people weren't clear to get married,
for instance, or that membership
might need to take a little more time,
or that there might need to be 2 or 3 or 4 meetings
faced that over a number of months before
we get at the clearness part of things.
I think that's helpful in a couple of ways.
It's helpful in the "yes", like of,
"Ah, yes, like this was a leading, so okay self-doubt
like, take that, there's a committee of other
friends who have listened and heard!".
It's also like,
I can rejoice in the "no".
Like, when a Clearance Ccommittee ends in a "wait",
or like, "That wasn't what I thought it was".
Then that's coming from God
and I can feel so much more comfortable
in that "no" or in that "wait"
than just like, "Well I really said no, or wait,
but it was just like my own self-doubt".
That's gone.
That's kinda out of the picture
at the end of a Clearness Committee.
Sometimes you don't come to clarity,
so that's kind of a bummer when that happens.
But it definitely is not uncommon,
so if that happens to you, don't worry,
you're not a failure at Quakerism.
You can try again or
you can allow the wisdom that did emerge
out of that community to inform your decision.
In this space of faithful waiting and listening,
and frankly listening with love
for the person who has the question,
means that when we bring that love together
in the different ways each individual holds that,
even if no clarity comes from it,
there is a sense of being held in love by our community
that can make the lack of clarity
not as scary as it used to be.