And so Woolman traveled the East Coast for almost 20 years
sharing what he felt had been laid upon him
by the Lord about the evils of slavery.
He was famous for appearing in
for wearing undyed clothing, plain white clothing,
because the dyned was a product of slave labor.
And he was famous for showing up at a farmhouse at night
and if he learned that the meal had been prepared by
or if it was being served by a slave,
he would fast while he stayed a table,
so he was utterly consistent with his message
in both his words and in his actions.
And after 20 years of this witnessing,
this mirroring back to this holding up
of a mirror where people could,
while they were eating the meal
that a slave had prepared or served.
Woolman was speaking of fundamental Quaker beliefs
and not haranguing that just witnessing testify.
After 20 years of this,
Quakers reached consensus on freeing their slaves.
Now the important point in this story is
not only the way he held up a mirror to
people's lives patiently over a long period of time,
but that Quakers were the first religious community
in the United States to free their slaves.
And they did so 80 years before the Civil War was fought.
It's a story that allows me to ask the question,
"Is patients always such a bad thing?",
that's slow sometimes mean faster
if what you're doing is going to the root system
rather than just putting wallpaper over a problem
and pretending that it's fixed.
I think there's a lot in organizational life
and a lot in our societal life that requires
that steady patient witnessing that
can help create long-lasting and deep-rooted change
around some of our most intractable issues,
whereas just taking a vote and getting it over with
as quickly as possible to relieve the tension really leaves,
leaves things untouched or prescribing the answer
and giving people the technique that will solve the problem
really leaves the deeper things untouched.