It takes a lot of patience to be in an organization this way.
Because we do have  in us is impulse
to control processes and quotes 'get results'.
And the  fixing mode that a lot of consultants get into,
looks on the surface like it's doing a better job
of controlling processes and getting results.
My sense is though that is often an illusion
that gets manufactured for a short period of time
and then things revert back to the status quo.
It takes more time in patients,
to be in that organization or in the world,
in an inquiry mode which helps people
see themselves in the mirror.
But once they've seen themselves,
the transformation is much more likely to
have legs to stand, to last, to make the distance.
There's actually a great story out of Quaker tradition
that I'd love to tell about this.
Because its historical fact and
I think it witnesses to the point I'm trying to make.
A hundred years before the Civil War was fought,
there were Quakers on the East Coast
who like everybody else owned slaves,
they were farmers and you ran a farm with slaves
that was the American economy.
And there was among within that Quaker community,
a man named John Wooloman,
who had it as he said laid upon him by the Lord
that slavery was evil and moral wrong.
And the Quakers,
that God was calling Quakers to free their slaves.
He took this to his local meeting, congregation.
And they wrestled with it in open dialogue.
And could not come to consensus
which is what Quakers have to do,
they don't take a vote,
because they think voting is violent
if 51% can tell 49% where to get off,
that's an act of violence.
And so they labored with it trying to reach consensus
but couldn't reach consensus.
But they said to John Woolman,
"While we don't yet have this light for ourselves,
we don't have any doubt
that you're  seeing something very clearly,
we just can't see it yet.
And so we will support  your family
while you travel among Quaker Friends
up and down the East Coast, delivering your message
sharing your revelation for as long as
it takes for some kind of outcome to happen.