But to cut to the chase, the Clearness Committee is
basically an inquiry model of being in the world.
And I like to say
especially that in academic setting that
what a Clearness Committee does with an individual
by way of inquiring honestly
and openly into who that individual is
and what that individuals inner teachers has to say.
It's the same posture that
a scholar adopts, a great scholar adopts
toward whatever it is that he or she is studying.
If you're a physicist you're not in the world
to locate a subatomic particle and then tell it
what it's supposed to be doing or tell it what its nature is.
Great physicists actually
listen to the thing they're trying to understand.
And they have such a passion
about understanding that thing on its own terms
without imposing false categories on it.
That they're very good listeners,
great scholars are always very good listeners,
because they have such reverence and respect
for whatever they are studying that
they want to hear  it into speech,
they wanted to speak to them in its own voice.
And the  puzzlement for me in universities
frankly has been why we know how to
extend that respect to subatomic
particles or bodies of literature or periods of history,
but we don't know how to respect to each other.
So the Clearness Committee is an opportunity
to do it for each other which seems right
and proper to me and fruitful life giving.
In organizational terms, I think
the Clearness Committee is like the
good leader who walks around basically saying,
"What's happening here?
And how are you experiencing what's happening?",
and listen very carefully in a way that
helps people hold a mirror up to themselves
and engage in that most remarkable
human activity called self-correction.
Just as you look at yourself in the mirror
to see that you are missing the mark.
Not because someone tells you that you're missing the mark,
but because you already know what the mark is.
And the mirror helps you see there you're off target.
There's a way I think of leading in an organization
or of helping an organization understand its own life.
That is much more about mirroring than it is
about advising, fixing, saving and setting everybody straight.
And mirroring is powerful, because when
people see themselvess in the mirror and
engage in that activity called
self-correction or self-analysis or self-understanding,
the results are much more likely to be permanent and deep
than they are when some outsider comes along and says,
"Oh, you got this all wrong,
better you should do it this way!",
which people may do for a week or two and then
they'll revert to whatever it is they're more comfortable with.