贵格会实践之洞察\n\n\n
Discernment is really the heart and the core
of everything we do as Friends.
It's the core of our practice in worship,
it's the core of our practice in worship
for business, it's the center of how we make
decisions in our lives, to marry, for our
employment, for our work in the world, for
our ministry.
The process of discernment and being called,
or having a leading or the deepest knowing.
All of those feel like incredibly connected, if
not the exact same thing.
For me, discernment is the core technology
of Quakerism.
It is the thing that we learn to do and that
our faith supports.
And that is to thresh through the complexity
of life and find the kernel, find the root,
find the way. The way for me today,
at this moment.
Some people may call it
seeking the will of God.
Others may call it consulting
their deep inner wisdom.
I think a lot of people do discernment relatively
spontaneously when they have a sticky issue
to deal with, and they stop, they let it rest
a while.
They let an answer rise up in them.
To tell the difference between the still
small voice that's guiding me well and the
many other voices, the many other fine, human
voices that are within me.
So, discernment is listening for God's will
for us to move us more fully into God's understanding
of the kingdom of heaven, of right order between
all creation, humans and plants and animals
and ideas, I would even say.
Of course, part of Quaker discernment is the
rational, reasonable assessment of the pros
and cons of the decision at hand.
Discernment takes it a step farther than that
and invites us to go to a deep place, a centered
place, and to see how. How where our rational
minds have led us, sits in us.
Discernment is accessing that place where
God is at work in us, and it's well beyond
rational, thoughtful, weighing of the situation.
It's not without an information gathering
phase where we have to understand the parameters
clearly, but then, after that, it comes down
to accessing that same place that vocal ministry
comes from, that place of deep faithfulness
where we don't care whether it's this or that.
We have no investment in which side of that
question we fall on, and: "God, what do you
want me to do here?"
And so then we listen with the reason, we
listen with emotion, we listen with inspiration,
and, kind of, more than a touch of hope.
And I'll say, experientially, I know that
it functions.
It works.
That when we trust one another, when we are
able to be vulnerable with one another, when
we allow ourselves to think that it might
actually be the case that God is an actual
thing that we might actually be able to hear
and might live into actually better lives,
well, and behold something happens in
that space.
So, discernment, for me, is definitely a listening,
but it also is this process
of allowing and letting go.